<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the oath of supremacy</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17363</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12656258</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12656258</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 677:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the oath of supremacy</title>
                  <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Roman Catholic tract written possibly by Peter Walsh.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE OATH OF SUPREMACY.</p>
            <p>Printed in the YEAR, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <div type="oath">
               <pb facs="tcp:65377:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:65377:2"/>
               <head>THE Words of the Oath.</head>
               <p>I A. B. <hi>do utterly testifie and declare in my conſcience, that the Kings Majeſty is the only Supream Governor of this Realm, and of all other His Highneſſes Dominions and Countries, as well in all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical things or cauſes, as Temporal: And that no Forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate hath or ougbt to have any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Pre-eminence, or Authority Eccleſiastical or Spiritual within this Realm: And therefore I do utterly renounce and forſake all Forreign Juriſdictions, Powers, Superiorities and Authorities: And do promiſe, that from henceforth I ſhall bear Faith &amp; true Allegiance to the Kings Highneſs, His Heirs and lawful Succeſſors, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Pre-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies and Authorities granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſs, His Heirs and Succeſſors, or united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm: So help me God, and by the Contents of this Book.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:65377:3"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65377:3"/>
               <head>Introduction.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> has long been thought, by the generality of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> Inconſiſtent with Faith, both for what it affirms of the <hi>King,</hi> and denies of the <hi>Pope.</hi> And truly, who conſiders only the Words, as they ly naked there, without ſeeking to inform himſelf what they mean of any thing but the bare ſounds, has reaſon at firſt ſight to check at it. I am apt to believe that every body does not look farther; at leaſt I my ſelf did not a great while, and therefore thought of it as others did.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet it ſeemed ſtrange, that the moſt Learned of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould freely take it without ſcruple; and at the ſame time Irreprehenſibly affirm, both of the <hi>Kings</hi> Power and the <hi>Popes,</hi> what <hi>Catholicks</hi> therefore refuſe the <hi>Oath,</hi> becauſe they think it denies. I perceived they muſt of neceſſity underſtand it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than We did. For to ſuſpect, that either of us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed otherwiſe than according to our conſcience, They in Taking, and VVe in Refuſing, is not either for a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, or Reaſonable Man. I would not handſomly unrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, when a miſtake there muſt needs be on one ſide, how the miſtake ſhould ly on theirs, or which way they ſhould miſunderſtand an <hi>Oath</hi> of their own making. In ſhort, I knew not what to make of it; and while I had no Key to the Lock, but the bare words, could not eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it. For ſtill thoſe words ſeemed Irreconcilable to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65377:4"/> Truth, and to that Truth which they profeſs, as well as that which I believe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Upon farther ſearch, things appeared ſomthing otherwiſe. I found, that what thoſe Learned Men mean when they ſwear, and which they think the VVords of the <hi>Oath</hi> mean, is not only ſutable to what they believe themſelves, but likewiſe to what we believe; and I found there is more Reaſon, than I imagined, to believe that the words of the <hi>Oath</hi> do indeed mean, as they judge they do, and not as VVe thought. VVhat occurs to me, I thought a ſeaſonable Charity to communicate to others, leſt by ſeeking to avoyd one Error we fall into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For, as we are on the one ſide obliged to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a good Conſcience before all Worldly reſpects, ſo we are obliged on the other, to obey our Soveraign and his Laws, where with a good conſcience we can. No Man can juſtify the refuſal of an <hi>Oath,</hi> tendred by Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority, without a ſufficient Reaſon. The Reaſon why we have refuſed this <hi>Oath,</hi> is, becauſe we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended it Inconſiſtent with Faith. And that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly a ſufficient Reaſon, if the apprehenſion be true; but if it be not, we are left in the Lurch. If the <hi>Oath,</hi> as ſome think, do not renounce the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>all Catholicks,</hi> but only the <hi>Opinions</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> and thoſe both falſe and pernicious, to refuſe it, is not to preſerve, but to ſcandalize our <hi>Faith,</hi> with the imputation of obliging us to things, by the Wiſdom of the Nation, judg'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. It is to confirm the bad opinion which ſome have of us, that our Religion is indeed Inconſiſtent with the ſecurity of the Commonwealth. In a word, what we took for Religion, would prove Faction.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Before I ſpeak of the <hi>Oath</hi> it ſelf, it will be convenient to obſerve, that divers priviledges have at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65377:4"/> divers times, been granted, by the Piety of Princes, to the Church, and Church-Men, when being long uſed, and their origin either forgotten or diſſembled, have at length been commonly enough lookt upon and claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the proper and inherent Right of the Church. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe is the right of holding Judiciary Pleas and Courts, proceeding like Secular Courts to Sentence, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Temporal and Corporal Puniſhments, as Fines, Impriſonment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Executing their Sentences by their own Officers, unleſs in caſe of Death; for which, whether for Form or Subſtance, the <hi>Prachiam Seculare,</hi> was uſually call'd upon. Theſe Courts were ſettled by little and little, and their Power was ſometimes more, ſometimes leſs, which variety remains to this day, as the Secular Power in ſeveral Nations concurs, more or leſs with them. But it became at laſt the general Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, that Eccleſiaſtical Perſons ſhould appear only in theſe Courts for all cauſes, and the Laity for ſome, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as had relation to the Law of God. The Judges there, being either Eccleſiaſtical Men themſelves, or acting by Commiſſion from them, the Courts got the Name of Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual Courts; the matters determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in them, of Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual matters, or cauſes; and their Power of Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual Power. But</p>
               <p n="6">6. When things had gone thus Time out of mind, and People ſaw them conſtantly act, not by renewed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, as Subordinate Officers uſe to do, but by a Right of their own, a Right charily preſerved by them, and freely confeſt by every body els, as undoubtedly it was, both by a good Title at firſt, and a quiet poſſeſſion of many Hundred Years; it came to be thought at laſt, that this Right of theirs was given them with their Character by <hi>God;</hi> whereas in Truth it proceeded from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendence of Pious <hi>Men;</hi> and, as all Humane things
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65377:5"/> are ſubject to change, may, by the ſame Power which gave it, on juſt occaſion be taken away.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the mean time the Notion of <hi>Spiritual,</hi> when applyed in the <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>Power, Judge, Court, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> has generally relation to theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Courts. The word is ordinarily taken ſo in our common Language, but <hi>there</hi> ſeldome otherwiſe, and when we find it in the <hi>Law,</hi> we muſt expect it ſhould ſignify as it uſes to do in the Law, not as it does in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, or Controverſy, or Aſcetics. It is ſo well known, that I know not whether it be not idle to mention the different Significations which the ſame words have in different Occaſions. For example, who thinks of the Theological vertue, when he is to ſwear <hi>Faith</hi> to his Prince? who of a Stone or Tree, when he hears of a <hi>Body,</hi> not in Philoſophy but Phyſick? and when a Man of buſineſs is talking of a <hi>Material</hi> action or conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, He would be thought ſtrangely to rove, who ſhould fancy <hi>Material</hi> there ſignifyed as among Metaphyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The frequency of ſuch caſes made it neceſſary, that People might underſtand one another, to ſettle a Rule for the underſtanding of words, and eſtabliſh this maxime, that they be alwayes underſtood <hi>Secundum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectam Materiam</hi> as they phraſe it, according to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of which they ſpeak. I cannot tell, whether this Rule have alwayes been remembred in the caſe of this <hi>Oath:</hi> but doubt that who forgets it any where, hazards to perplex himſelf into inextricable confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65377:5"/>
               <head>Section I. <hi>Of the Affirmative Clauſe of the</hi> OATH.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis premiſed, I come to the <hi>Oath,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts Principally of two Clauſes; One <hi>Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> the other <hi>Negative;</hi> according to which, the reſt which have any ſhew of difficulty, are to be underſtood. The <hi>Affirmative</hi> acknowledges the King to be <hi>the only Supreme Governour of this Realm, and the reſt of his dominions, as well in all Spiritual or Eccleſiastical things or cauſes; as Temporal.</hi> By this clauſe it was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not only by <hi>Catholicks,</hi> but others too, that the King was inveſted with Power to do all that a Supreme pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual Governour could do, <hi>Preach, Confer Orders, Administer the Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. Which as it is evidently falſe, ſo 'tis evident likewiſe, that 'tis not the meaning of the Clauſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For, <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> being enjoyned by Law, for the acknowledgment of what was re-ſetled by Law in the King, it's words muſt bear the ſenſe they uſe to do, in Law-Language, and Law-Books, which according to what has been ſaid before, is, that the King is Supreme Governour of this Realm; So that who ever hath any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65377:6"/> ſhare in the Government of it, be he Spiritual or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Man, hath it from and under the King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe words being in two Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, whoſe declared ſenſe is, to reſtore what was due to the Crown, ought ſo to be underſtood as to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, <hi>all</hi> and <hi>no more</hi> in the King, then thoſe two Acts, either in themſelves, or in thoſe of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> revived by them, reſtored to him: ſince no more at moſt, and perchance not all of them, are ordered to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and conſequently ſenſe, of this <hi>Oath.</hi> Now, what was reſtored by theſe, every diligent Reader of them, will find to be only what may, without injury to Gods Law, be poſſeſs'd by the King.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For to begin, with King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> in the firſt of them, <hi>viz. Stat.</hi> 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 9. He only claims, or exerciſes the Power of ordering, where citations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Spiritual Courts of this Realm ſhall be made, which may be ſeen to be evidently his due. In the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond (24 K. <hi>H. 8th. C.</hi> 12.) he takes Power, only to order that no appeals in matters of <hi>Wills, Marriages, Divorces, Tithes, Oblations,</hi> and <hi>Obventions,</hi> ſhall be made out of this Realm; alleadging for reaſon, that as to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral part of them, they belong to the Imperial Crown, and, as to what in them may concern the Law of God, to the Clergy of this Realm, as being of parts fit for it; to whom he expreſly leaves this part, not aſſuming it to himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the <hi>3d. (Stat.</hi> 25. <hi>C.</hi> 20.) He uſes the Power to reſtrain the payment of Annats, and firſt-Fruits to <hi>Rome,</hi> (to which Temporal Power extends) and with his Biſhops in Parliament, orders how others are to be elected, and conſecrated by them; which <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings uſe to do.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the <hi>4th.</hi> (25. <hi>C.</hi> 9.) The Power which he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65377:6"/> is, that no new Canon-Laws ſhall be made, or old ones ſtand, without his approbation. Which he may have as a <hi>Knowing Man;</hi> they being things of human inſtitution; nay, as a <hi>Prince,</hi> he ought to have, ſince 'tis known, that Canon Laws do often claſh with the Laws of the Realm. Though, if he abuſes this Power, by hindering good Laws, and unprejudicial to the State, He is to anſwer for that; though to God alone.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the <hi>5th.</hi> (25. K. <hi>H. c.</hi> 21.) He takes Power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Paying of Money to <hi>Rome;</hi> to hinder the <hi>Pope</hi> from Diſpenſing in Human Spiritual Laws: to diſpenſe in them Himſelf by his Biſhops; and with his Parliament to annul them. All which, certainly he may do as King. And that he intended here to do no more than he might do, appears by a <hi>Proviſo</hi> of this Act, revived by Q. <hi>E.</hi> and afterwards to be Cited.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In the <hi>6th.</hi> (26. <hi>C.</hi> 14.) He only aſſigns Suffragans by conſent of Biſhops in Parliament: Which Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a thing of Human Inſtitution; and as it depends on the Law of the Land, may proceed from him. And, if it be ſaid by any, That, ſince Chriſt gave his Apoſtles Power to Preach where they ſhould pleaſe, and think fit, and ſo, that they have from Chriſt Power indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of any Law of the Land, (as in times of Heathen Emperors) to agree among themſelves, what Territories every one ſhall have to do his Duty in; which the King cannot take from them, as he may ſeem here to do: 'Tis reply'd, That They may agree among themſelves, to have what Territories the Law or King ſhall aſſign them. And thus, at leaſt, the King may without Injury, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with their Conſents) aſſign them Dioceſs's, as well as the Legiſlators in <hi>England,</hi> and in Forreign Countries, divide one Pariſh into two, or compound two into one, as occaſion invites; without the leaſt Danger apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65377:7"/> of violating Faith; or (to ſpeak more properly) tranſgreſſing any Divine Inſtitution. And that it was done with their Conſents, is evident; becauſe here They did agree to it in Parliament: Or it may be ſaid, That They themſelves in Parliament did this. And the Laity agreed with them, to make it the Law of the Land.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In the <hi>7th.</hi> (28. <hi>C.</hi> 16.) He takes Power to give thoſe Temporal Gifts, which the <hi>Pope</hi> formerly gave; to put Biſhops into their Biſhopricks, Curates into their Cures, (as <hi>Catholick</hi> Princes now do) and to give them leave to do their Duties, not as to the purely Spiritual, Intrinſical Power in common; but as to ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances belonging to the Exerciſe of it, and commodious for the Subject: So as they ſhould have it from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not from <hi>Rome.</hi> Which he might lawfully do, as is juſt now explicated, and alſo make a Law they ſhould not have it from <hi>Rome,</hi> it being not neceſſary They ſhould; They having Power from Chriſt to Preach e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, till they limited their Territories by their own Conſent; and here diſſent from doing it at the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In the <hi>8th.</hi> He takes Power to make a Civil Law, as to Degrees of Marriages. And, if as he did this, he judg'd what was of Faith in the Caſe; he did it not, as ſent by Chriſt, but, as a Schollar Authoriz'd by Law, which he may alſo do; or, as pre-inform'd by his Biſhops.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>9th.</hi> and laſt, He only makes a Civil Order concerning the Marriage of Doctors of the Civil Law.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Title of Q. <hi>E</hi>'s. firſt Act (made 1. <hi>El.</hi> c. 1.) being an <hi>Act reſtoring to the Crown the Antient Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over the State Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual, and aboliſhing all Forreign Power, repugnant to the ſame:</hi> evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes, that what ſhe took, was in <hi>Catholick</hi>-Times due to the Crown; And Poſſeſt by Gift or Uſurpation from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65377:7"/> it, till ſhe took it back. For ſhe could not call what might be due, only ſince the <hi>22th.</hi> Year of her Father's Reign, <hi>Antient Juriſdiction.</hi> And ſince purely Spiritual Juriſdiction was not then in the Crown, it could not be in her Time reſtored to it. The Preamble alſo ſpeaks of K. <hi>H.</hi> 8's. reſtoring Antient (to wit, in reſpect of his Times) Juriſdictions <hi>of Right belonging,</hi> &amp;c. which could be only thoſe of <hi>Catholick</hi> Times. More-over, By this Preamble (which contains the Deſign of the whole Act) praiſing K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> for taking away from the <hi>Pope</hi> what Power he had Uſurped, and reſtoring it to the Crown, diſpraiſing Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> for un-doing what he had done in this, and deſiring a Remedy; or that Things be brought into the ſtate, in which K. <hi>H.</hi> put them; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by this Acts reviving the afore-ſaid Nine Statutes, it ſeems evident, that this Act intended to give the Queen no more, than the Revived Acts gave <hi>him;</hi> giving her here in general Words, (and the ſame is to be ſaid of taking away from the <hi>Pope)</hi> and at once, what thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Acts gave by parts. Now, that they gave him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Natural, Temporal, Earthly, or Civil Power, and not any Super-natural, derived from the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; we have ſeen by numbring up all Particulars given, and finding ever one of them to be but Temporal; and we may alſo find, by reflecting, that he declares in the Preamble to the Second of them, That he intended to do more fully, what ſeveral <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings had done in part. And this is clearly confirm'd, by ſeeing in particular, what it was, which this Act, when it comes to Eſtabliſh, doth Eſtabliſh in her: For we ſee the Particulars mentioned are only, <hi>Power for the Viſitation of the Eccleſiaſtical State and Perſons,</hi> (to wit, to the end that ſhe might know their Faults) and for the <hi>Puniſhment of all ſuch Faults.</hi> And as for giving Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65377:8"/> or Eccleſiaſtical Power, 'tis already ſeen, to be in our Law-Books, but Human.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Preſently after this, the Act tells us; That the End deſign'd to be brought about by the Oath, is the Maintenance of the Act, or the acknowledging what is in it Eſtabliſhed. And hence, except we are ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as to think, that the Oath was deſign'd for the Maintenance of this, and ſome thing elſe, not ſpoken of; and for want of its Knowledg that way, not to be maintained or acknowledged, (ſince no Man can main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or acknowledg a Poſition he doth not know of) we muſt ſay, That the Words of the Oath ſignify no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all more in the King, than the Acts give him. Since then 'tis by the Conſideration of all Particulars given, evident, that the Act, neither by its ſelf, nor by the Acts revived in it, gives the King any Power, as from Chriſt, to preach Chriſt's Doctrine, perſwade Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and help them, by giving them the Sacraments, to practiſe thoſe Parts of it: 'Tis alſo evident, that the Words of the Oath ſignify no ſuch thing in him.</p>
               <p n="13">13. It only remains, to ſee whether the one other Act, made (5. <hi>E.</hi> cap. 1.) concerning this Matter and Oath, gives her any more than this former. What repreſents it ſelf firſt to our View, is its Title, which runs thus: An <hi>Act for the Aſſurance of the Queens Majeſties Royal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over all States and Subjects within her Dominions.</hi> Now that <hi>[Royal]</hi> is no more than <hi>Human,</hi> every Body that underſtands both theſe Words, knows. Next, comes the Act it ſelf in all its Particulars, doing what the Title ſpeaks, and no more. For, firſt; For Conſervation of the Queen, and the Dignities of the Crown; and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſeveral Miſchiefs proceeding from the uſurped Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> it makes the Maintaining of this, <hi>Premunire</hi> and <hi>Treaſon;</hi> and to hinder the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65377:8"/> of this, becauſe it did thoſe Human Miſchiefs, for thoſe Human Good's ſake, What is it elſe but aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Royall Power? <hi>Secondly,</hi> It makes a Law, that the Senſe which the Queens Admonition gives the Oath, ſhall be its Senſe. And that this gives her only <hi>a Regal</hi> Power, we ſhall here after clearly ſee. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> and (as to our purpoſe) Laſtly, It makes a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> to exempt the Temporal Lords from this Oath, and any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in this Act. And why doth it do this? It ſayes expreſly; Becauſe her Majeſty was otherwiſe aſſured of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance.</hi> Which would have been no good Reaſon, in caſe ſhe had required more than Faith and Allegiance to be given her: For though ſhe had been aſſured of theſe, yet for the Aſſurance of that other thing, which ſhe requires to be given her, ſhe might have caus'd them to take the Oath, and not have exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them from it.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Our Aſſertion may be confirmed, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Oath ſayes not barely, That ſhe is the <hi>Supreme Governour in all Cauſes Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical;</hi> where <hi>Supreme Governour</hi> might poſſibly be in Senſe the ſame as <hi>Supreme Preacher:</hi> but expreſly, that ſhe is the <hi>Supreme Governour of the Realm</hi> in all ſuch cauſes. And ſince <hi>Supreme Governour of a Realm</hi> is in common, and indeed all ſpeech, the ſame exactly as <hi>Temporal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> the Oath only ſayes, That ſhe is the Supreme <hi>Temporal Governour</hi> in all Spiritual Things: Which it would be Treaſon to deny her, not only in all thoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eccleſiaſtical Things, of which only we have ſhew'd the Oath to ſpeak in the Common Senſe of thoſe Words, as they are us'd in Law: But alſo, in the moſt Spiritual Thing that can be imagin'd; as in the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Trinity, Incarnation, and the like. For ſhe is by her Office, the Temporal Rewarder of this Vertue, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65377:9"/> Puniſher of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s contrary Vice; which is to be a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Governour, as to this Vertue and Vice.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe ſhe ſayes expreſly in her <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> (in which ſhe calls it an Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and not <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> thereby ſhewing, that ſhe required no more, than <hi>Allegiance</hi> by it; except we will ſay, It is an Oath of <hi>more,</hi> than <hi>ſhe</hi> ſaid it was, who beſt underſtood it) that ſhe took <hi>only</hi> what K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> and K. <hi>Ed. 6th.</hi> took; to wit, in the Acts which ſhe liked and reviv'd; and not in Acts which ſhe diſlik'd, with what was taken in them; and therefore repeal'd, as is moſt reaſonable to underſtand her: Eſpecially ſince ſhe adds, leſt we ſhould miſtake her, to take any thing that in them might ſeem Uncatholick; <hi>And what was of Antient</hi> (which is the ſame as <hi>Catholick) time due to the Crown.</hi> Now, what K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> took, which only is to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (all that K. <hi>Ed. 6th.</hi> might do remaining by her Repealed) we have largely, and I think fully ſeen to be only Temporal. Nay, one may probably gueſs by his <hi>Inſtitution of a Chriſtian Man,</hi> (to be ſeen in the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Loyalty,</hi> a Book lately ſet forth, and that King's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (to be found in the <hi>Cabala)</hi> to the Clergy of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire)</hi> that he took no more even in the Repeal'd Acts, concerning his Headſhip of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church. Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly Biſhop <hi>Fiſher,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> might be the more Jealous of his being Head of the Church; becauſe They never ſaw that Book, it being ſet forth ſome Years after their Death? But that King <hi>Henry 8th.</hi> did not confound Regal and Paſtoral Power, purely Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, appears by his Book of Ordination; wherein he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that Paſtoral Authority (he means purely Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual) was by Ordination only committed to Men; and alſo, by his Injunctions: And therefore, could not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſuch kind of Paſtoral Authority, or that which is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65377:9"/> purely Spiritual to himſelf; nor Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> neither, who took no more than he did. But beſides, ſhe farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains her ſelf in expreſs Words, not to take the Power <hi>Of Adminiſtring Divine Service in the Church;</hi> but the <hi>Soveraignty and Rule over all Perſons, of what State ſoever they be;</hi> And what can be deſired clearer than this, for her not taking Power to Preach, Perſwade, and Help Chriſtians, as Chriſt bid his Apoſtles do; which is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words, to adminiſter Divine Service in the Church? And what is Power over Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, without Power in Eccleſiaſtical Functions, but Power <hi>Quantum per legem Dei licet</hi> (with which Addition Biſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi> himſelf agreed to the Title of <hi>Supreme Head</hi> of the Church) added by Act of Parliament, in the Confirmation of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Expoſition.</p>
               <p>And that the ſaid Words, <hi>[Supreme Governour of this Realm, and of all other His Highneſs</hi>'s <hi>Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> taking them all together, as they ly, (as we ought) can never ſignify other than a <hi>Civil Governour;</hi> what-ever <hi>Things</hi> or <hi>Cauſes</hi> his Power is expreſt to be in, appears farther by this, that thoſe Words are a very unſutable and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per title for any purely <hi>Spiritual Head.</hi> For, who-ever heard the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Roan</hi> (for example) call'd, <hi>Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all his Province of</hi> Normandy, <hi>in all Things or Cauſes purely Spiritual?</hi> Or, How would <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Princes take it, to have the <hi>Pope</hi> write himſelf, <hi>[Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all his Dominions or Countries, throughout the whole</hi> Catholick-<hi>Church, in purely Spiritual Affairs?]</hi> Theſe Words then will not ſuffer themſelves to be meant of any other Power, than that of a <hi>Civil Magiſtrate;</hi> nor can they, without much ſtraining them from their common Uſe, ſignify, that he aſſumes to Himſelf any thing, properly belonging to any Biſhop or Prieſt; and ſo, they have no ſhew of touching any thing concerv'd to be of Faith.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65377:10"/>
               <p>Again, The King of <hi>Spain</hi> has and exerciſes <hi>Supreme Spiritual Authority,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Sicily;</hi> which are as harſh Words, as any in the Oath: And yet all Chriſtendom knows, and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and Court of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, that that King claims a Governourſhip or Power, call'd <hi>Spiritual,</hi> (nay, and which is much more, <hi>Supremely ſuch)</hi> without any ones Fancying, that Faith is prejudic'd by ſuch a Title. Nor imports it, whether that King have this <hi>Spiritual Juriſdiction</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> or no: We have nothing to do with their Bargains; our only Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion at preſent, is concerning the meaning of the Word <hi>[Spiritual,]</hi> when apply'd to Kings; which, if it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Power <hi>purely Spiritual,</hi> could never have been given him by the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, without Creating him <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Now, I would ask upon this occaſion, Whether, if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had thought fitting to Command his Subjects in <hi>Sicily,</hi> to take an Oath of Supremacy, expreſt in theſe Words; That he is <hi>Supreme Spiritual Monarch,</hi> or has <hi>Supreme Spiritual Authority</hi> in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; whether it could ſtand with the Duty of his Subjects there, to refuſe to obey him, and to take it, upon a Caprichious Conceit, grounded on the double Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which the Words <hi>(Spiritual Supremacy)</hi> may poſſibly bear; and thence take ſhadow, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Faith? or, Whether ſuch a whimſy ought to excuſe them? I conceive, no good States-Man, though never ſo good a Chriſtian, would think him blameleſs. You'l ſay, 'Tis a different Caſe. I add then this forcible Reaſon, which I am ſure is unanſwerable.</p>
               <p>If the Words <hi>[In Spiritual or Eccleſiastical Things or Cauſes]</hi> ſubjoyn'd to <hi>[Supreme Governour,</hi> &amp;c.] wrong Faith; that is, if thoſe Words give the King a <hi>Power purely Spiritual,</hi> as is feared and objected; then the word <hi>[ONLY]</hi> joyn'd to <hi>[Supreme Governour,]</hi> and <hi>[ALL]</hi> to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65377:10"/> 
                  <hi>[Things or Cauſes]</hi> being ſo Ample and Extenſive, muſt either give him the <hi>whole Latitude</hi> of Power <hi>purely Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual;</hi> or <hi>None at all,</hi> but <hi>All</hi> Power of ſome <hi>Other</hi> kind: But it muſt coſt us the Forfeiture of Common Senſe to imagin, that either the Oath makers ſhould intend to <hi>Give,</hi> or the King to <hi>Receive</hi> the <hi>whole Latitude</hi> of Power <hi>purely Spiritual;</hi> For then he muſt have Power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Orders, conſecrate the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> abſolve in Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which no Chriſtian ever attributed to a Secular Magiſtrate: Therefore, 'tis evident, thoſe Words do not give the King any Power or Supremacy <hi>purely Spiritual</hi> at all; nor conſequently can they breed the leaſt Scruple in any Perſon of Loyal Principles, that they concern or ſhock Faith.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Theſe Things ſeem evident enough: How-ever, for a <hi>5th.</hi> Proof and Explication of many Things that have been ſaid, concerning what K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> took upon him in the Reviv'd Acts, (that make the ſame belong to our King, and be by us in this Oath acknowledg'd as his due, or annext to his Crown) let us conſider, that the Power ſo proper to a Paſtor, that we cannot give it to our Prince, is nothing elſe, but a Man's being by our Saviour's Appointment, Immediate (to his Apoſtles,) or Mediate (to their Succeſſors) deputed to Preach his Faith, Perſwade, and (in the Sacraments) help the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it; and by that Deputation, enabled to do theſe Things. Whereas a Lay-man, out of Charity and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to another, or any other Good Motive, beſides our Saviour's Appointment, (which he hath not, in our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that he is a Lay-man or not Appointed; and ſo would Uſurp, if he pretended to it) may teach him his Catechiſm, or ſend a Paſtor, that is his Friend, or his Chaplain, to do it: And out of the ſame, and other Reaſonable Motives, the King may have a <hi>Human</hi> Power
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65377:11"/> either to teach a Man, if he pleaſes, or ſend all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that are Paſtors, to do their Duties, or exerciſe the Power Chriſt gave them; Nay, and to hinder them from exerciſing of it, in caſe (of Wicked Life, for example) it be unreaſonable they ſhould; ſince the Law can prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and puniſh any unreaſonable Thing or Vice; and ſince the Paſtor himſelf, though he hath the Power, ought not then to exerciſe it. And as the King may order them to do their Duties apart, ſo in Counſel: And as he may, out of thoſe ſaid Motives, Teach; ſo he may out of the ſame, <hi>as a knowing Chriſtian Man,</hi> judge what he ought to Teach, or judge what is Faith, what is Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; likewiſe, what is or is not a convenient Canon-Law, or a fit Prayer to be uſed in his Churches, and the like. And more than theſe we do not find, that the Acts ever gave K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> I believe it will be found, that <hi>Solomon,</hi> at the Dedication of the Temple, and the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> did as much or more; as in reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abuſes in God's Worſhip, pulling down Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Idolatry, and the like; and yet none imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they in ſo doing uſurp't the Office of the High-Prieſt, as ſacredly reſerved to him then, by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi>'s, or that of Biſhops is now to them.</p>
               <p n="17">17. To theſe Examples, I know it is commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, That theſe Kings did not do theſe Things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out uſurping the Prieſt's Office, in caſe they did more than Execute what the Prieſts judg'd to be the Law of God, and its Convenient Practice: It being not the King's, but Prieſt's Office, to judge what was the Law of God, to Teach it to the People, and perſwade them to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it. And hence, that they reach not King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Caſe, who was impower'd with Sixteen of the Clergy, and Sixteen of the Laity, to judge what Canons were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65377:11"/> not repugnant to the Law of God, (as in 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 19.) and in his Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> to judge of Appeals from Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Courts: Nor Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Caſe, who took upon her to order a New Form of Prayer, and a New Manner of Conſecrating Prieſts and Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="18">18. But this Reply invalidates not the Application of theſe Examples. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe in the Preamble of the Statute 24. <hi>C.</hi> 12. the Judgment of Things concerning the Law of God and Divinity, is left to the Clergy, as a thing of their (and not the Laity's) Office: By which it appears, that the King no more acted out of ſuch an Office in himſelf, than the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings did. And the ſame Office Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> denyes to her ſelf in her Admonition; and ſo leaves it, and its Exerciſes to the Clergy. And this is alſo evident, becauſe no Power is given to either of them by Act, (which only concerns us) to order concerning the Law of God, or its Practice, without the Clergy's ordering it, with them. For in the Firſt, Sixteen Clergy-Men are mentioned: In the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Spiritual Court, if the Matter belonged to it, Judged Firſt: And though an Appeal lay to the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, 'twas not the Chancery, but Commiſſioners, who were to judge of that Appeal; which Commiſſioners, if the Caſe concern'd the Law of God, 'tis to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, were to be Clergy-Men; as we ſhall ſee by and by. Likewiſe, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> left the making of the Common-Prayer, and Form of Conſecration to Clergy-Men. And hence, they were never hindred from doing their Office, that Chriſt gave them Power to do: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did our Princes by theſe Laws pretend to do it; but do what they did by the Clergies Directions, as far as they judg'd them to direct right.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Hence I Reply, <hi>Secondly,</hi> according to what has been ſaid already, That though no Lay-Man can be a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65377:12"/> Judge of what is Faith, or a Preacher of it, (to which are reduced an Excommunicator, or Denouncer of him that doth contrary to it, or its Practice, as of a Man to be avoyded; and a Maker of Laws or Directions for its beſt Practice, without any other Force, than that of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication) in the moſt common or moſt proper Senſe of theſe VVords; which is the ſame, as a <hi>Judge or Preacher authoriz'd, or made by Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Immediate or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Appointment:</hi> Yet if the Word <hi>[Judge]</hi> be uſed to ſignify no more, than one that knows or judges what is true Faith, or its beſt Practice, by Natural Reaſon, not Authoritative Miſſion, in this Senſe, every Lay-Man is and ought to be Judge of Faith, and of its Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers too; becauſe every Man has, and ought to uſe his Reaſon in Faith, as well as every thing elſe: And he ſeeing many ſorts of Faith pretended to be Chriſt's, and many ſorts of Preachers pretending to be True Ones, is this way to judge of both theſe, by the Reaſons they bring for themſelves, and their Faith. And hence, the King, as a <hi>Chriſtian Man,</hi> is in this Senſe a <hi>Judge</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> Nay, in a particular Manner, as he is <hi>King.</hi> For, as <hi>King,</hi> he ought to uſe the Power he hath, to ſee that Chriſt's true Faith be believ'd and practiz'd by his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And, how can he ſee that Laws be made and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for this, without he knows or judges which it is? Or, how can he put in True, and put out Falſe Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, without he knows by more than their own Words; which are ſo? And, how can he eſtabliſh right Laws for its Practice, and aboliſh wrong Ones, except he judge which are Good Ones, which not? Neither do I by this Power given to Princes of Judging in Matters of Faith, give them that Power of Judgment, which is proper to the <hi>Church.</hi> Chriſt delivered his Doctrine not to Princes, but Paſtors; and commanded Them (not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65377:12"/> Princes) to Teach the Flock, and all the Flock: Princes, as well as private Men, to hear their Voice. Yet Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the many Things, which fall under a Princes Care, and about which he muſt needs Act one way or other; I conceive, he cannot Act in any thing, without Judgment; and ſo muſt of Neceſſity judge <hi>his</hi> way, <hi>of Faith,</hi> if he Act about Faith. But, the Church judges, in order to Teach the Faithful; the Prince, in order to Govern his Subjects, and appoint Rewards or Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. We hold the Church Infallible; and therefore, She can oblige People to Interior Aſſent. The Prince may happen to judge wrong; which, if he do, we are not bound to Believe as he Judges: Though we are bound to ſubmit, and patiently ſuffer the Penalties, to which that wrong Judgment may expoſe us. Other Differences there are, which it is to no purpoſe to mention.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Likewiſe, If the Word <hi>[Preacher]</hi> ſignify no more, than one that Teaches another what he knows of Chriſt's Doctrine, and it's right Practice; then a Lay-Man may, without Injury to the Clergy, be a Preacher: witneſs, <hi>Apollo</hi> in the <hi>Acts;</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith, and diſproving Hereſies, and writing Devout Treatiſes; Parents, in reſpect of their Children; and God-Fathers, in reſpect of their God-Children. More-over, What Injury would it have been, if Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> had been made ſuch a Writer or Preacher by Act of Parliament? And the ſame may be ſaid of a <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Queen,</hi> who either by Themſelves or Counſel, may be Learn'd enough. Nay, though every <hi>King</hi> be not a Preacher by Writing, or Speaking; yet he is a Supreme Authoritative Preacher in his kind, ſince he by eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Faith, and its Practice, before another, both Teaches, and perſwades to Practiſe it: and in this way he hath none above him. And ſince all (properly call'd)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65377:13"/> Preachers here, have Leave or Juriſdiction from Chriſt, and from our Law, he ſupremely gives them the Later: Much more, the Juriſdiction they have to make Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Laws, to judge thoſe that do againſt them, and execute their Sentence. And in this we have ſeen, how the King, as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> may be Judge and Teacher of Faith; and that Authorized by the Law of the Land: How, as a King, he may, and ought to be Supreme Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Judge of what Faith ought to be eſtabliſh't by Law, and the Supreme of thoſe that Preach (or cauſe People to Believe and Practice) by eſtabliſhing Faith, its Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſent by Chriſt, and their Directive Laws by Law; and by giving them the Juriſdiction they may have from Law, to do what Chriſt bid them; laſtly, how he is the Supreme Giver of Power, to make Civil Laws, to Judge by them, and Execute them.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is in Truth, more Aſſumed in the Objection, than there is warrant for in the Act mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It does not appear there, that the King is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd to judge of the Repugnance of Canons to the Law of God: On the contrary, it ſeems meant, that that Matter ſhould be left to the Clergy: For, why elſe ſhould Sixteen of them be put into Commiſſion? Neither are the Words, on which the Objection is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch Canons ſhall be retained, as <hi>ſhall be approved to ſtand with the Laws of God,</hi> &amp;c. the Words of the Parliament, but of the Clergy themſelves; who cannot be thought to mean by them, that the Laity ſhould be Judges of the Law of God. They are only recited by the Parliament; which, when it comes to do its own part, uſes other Expreſſions. There are other Reaſons, why the King ſhould interpoſe: The Reaſon of the Act is aſſigned to be, becauſe <hi>Divers Conſtitutions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be thought, not only to be much Prejudicial to the King's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65377:13"/> Royal, and Repugnant to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, but alſo over-much onerous to his Highneſs and his Subjects.</hi> Of thoſe things who can Judge ſo well as the King, with the Aſſiſtance of ſome of the Laity, beſt verſed in the Laws of the Land? Again, the King was to add his Authority to thoſe Canons, to make them Binding; and therefore, muſt needs know, what he ſhould Authorize, and ſee why he ſhould do it. And this is all the Power in him, which can be Collected from this Statute. As for Appeals, the Act indeed orders they ſhould, for lack of Juſtice in other Courts, be made in Chancery; but not determined there, but by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to be granted by the King, that all Differences of his Subjects be finally determin'd by his Authority. But 'tis not ſaid, nor is to be ſuppoſed, that thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions ſhall be granted to the Laity, where the Caſe concerns the Law of God. For, Appeals are ordered by this Act, to be as was directed by a former Act of the ſame Parliament, <hi>An.</hi> 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. By which Act, where any Cauſe of the Law-Divine, or Spiritual Learning hapned to come in queſtion, the Body-Spiritual of the Realm is declared to be Qualifyed, and to have Power to determin it; and therefore, to them it muſt needs be meant to be left.</p>
               <p>To return to our Matter again, Since thoſe Parliaments evidently knew, their King was neither Biſhop nor Prieſt; which even in their Thoughts was the ſame, as not to have Power to Act in Spiritual Things, by our Saviour's immediate or mediate Supernatural Miſſion; or, which is the ſame thing, by the Power of the Keys: They evidently ſaw, he neither had, nor could have, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Paſtoral Power, purely Spiritual; much leſs, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power of that kind, what-ever the Supremacy of that kind conſiſts in. Hence, they could never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65377:14"/> to give him, what they ſaw he could not have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him; nor ſignify any ſuch Gift, or Senſe, by their Words in the Act or Oath; But only a Gift of the above-explicated Power, ariſing from Nature and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. A Legal Power to exerciſe which, as a Governor, they knew he might have from them; and to ſay, that they intended to flatter him, with the Acknowledgment of a Power in him, which they knew was not in him, is a Fault, that they cannot be prov'd Guilty of, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we remember their <hi>Proviſo):</hi> And ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Axiom, <hi>Every one is to be preſumed Good, till he be prov'd to be Bad;</hi> they ought to be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p n="23">23. Wherefore upon the whole, it is many wayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that the Words in the Affirmative Part of the Oath, cannot mean any thing but Supremacy of the Sword; which, whether in Temporal or Spiritual Things, cannot be exercis'd but by Authority deriv'd from the King. And this Supremacy is ſo evidently His, that He needed not this Act for it: He has it from God and Nature; and, as it is inſeparable from the Crown, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had it, even when Eccleſiaſtical Authority was at the Higheſt. For, though the Biſhops claim'd an Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Power of their own; yet, as Things do not ceaſe to be, by not being acknowledged, They truly acted under him, and in vertue of his Allowance, and ſubject to his Controll. When-ever he pleaſed to interpoſe, as the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <hi>Mortmain, Proviſions, Premunire,</hi> and the reſt made in <hi>Catholick</hi> Times, ſhew he often did, His Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Laws carry'd it, notwithſtanding their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
               <p n="24">24. That they did mean only thus, is, beyond all doubt, apparent by all manner of wayes, by which any thing can appear. And though what hath been already
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65377:14"/> ſaid out of the Oath it ſelf, and all the Acts, which are any way ordered to Eſtabliſh the Duties to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by it, ſeem to force a Perſwaſion, that only <hi>Royal</hi> Power is required to be own'd by the Affirmative Clauſe. I cannot leave this Part, till I put the <hi>Reader</hi> in mind, leſt he ſhould ſuſpect theſe Reaſons Fallacious, as ſeeming good Ones only to my ſelf, how both Learned <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-Church, underſtand this to be the Senſe of it. I alledge then, that all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Authors, not one I think excepted, agree, That 'tis not the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Keys,</hi> but of the <hi>Sword,</hi> which is in the King: I could name ſeveral, but chuſe to mention only Doctor <hi>Bramhal,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh;</hi> becauſe no Body ſpeaks, or I think can ſpeak plainer: And what he ſayes, I take to be the Senſe of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> his Works being very lately Reprinted in one Volume, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated by the Biſhop of <hi>Limric</hi> to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin.</hi> In his <hi>Schiſm Garded,</hi> p. 311, 312. ſpeaking of this Act, he ſayes thus: <hi>In a Word, there is no Power aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to our King, but meerly Political and Coactive, to ſee that all their Subjects do their Duties in their ſeveral Places. Coactive Power is one of the Keys, of the Kingdom of this World; it is none of the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven. This might have been exprest in Words leſs ſubject to Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the Caſe is clear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25. Next, The 37. Article of the Church of <hi>England: Where we attribute to the King</hi>'s <hi>Majeſty, the Chief Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.—We give not to our Prince the Miniſtring either of God's Word, or the Sacraments, but that only Prerogative, which we ſee to have been given to all Godly Princes in Holy Scriptures by God himſelf: That is, That they ſhould Rule all Eſtates and Degrees committed to their Charge by God, whether they be Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal; and reſtrain with the Civil Sword the ſtubborn and evil Doers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65377:15"/>26. I could add here divers other Eminent, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly approved Authors, who are very full in expreſſing the ſame Senſe of the Oath; as Doctor <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dayes, Doctor <hi>Carlton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> in King <hi>James</hi>'s Time, (both cited at large by Mr. <hi>Creſſy</hi> in his <hi>Reflections upon the Oaths,</hi> Sect. 6.) and others: But I conceive, enough is ſaid to the clearing the Affirmative Clauſe of the Oath; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, they may be more proper here-after to explain the Negative Part of it, to which we now addreſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Section II. <hi>Of the Negative Clauſe of the</hi> OATH.</head>
               <p>THe Negative Clauſe runs thus: <hi>That no Forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Pre-eminence or Authority, Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, within this Realm.</hi> Now, though there want not ſome, who think, that taking the Words of the Oath in a Law-Senſe, and allowing Common Reaſon to ſcan the whole, &amp; not Fancy to catch ſuddainly at ſingle Words, the Oath, even as it lyes, may lawfully be taken by thoſe, who are able to penetrate throughly into it: Yet the Generality
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65377:15"/> (whom chiefly I muſt endeavour to ſatisfy) are more apt to judge, that if thoſe Words be taken in the full Latitude of what they ſeem firſt to ſound, they cannot be ſworn by any <hi>Catholick.</hi> And they have Reaſon. For it is plain, that no Human Authority can take away what is given by Chriſt. It is plain in Scripture, that Chriſt did give to his Apoſtles, and in them their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Power to Teach and Feed, to Bind and Loſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this over all the World. The Exerciſe of this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may be, and is reſtrained by Human Conſtitutions; becauſe, it being to Edification, not Deſtruction, 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt its Nature, to be us'd where 'twould do harm; as, if every Paſtor ſhould promiſcuouſly Feed every Flock, there would happen ſo much Confuſion and Diſorder, that a good part of the Sheep would be (not Fed, but) Starv'd. 'Tis this, which truly binds up the Power: Human Laws ſhew, and that Authoritatively and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingly, where the Harm is; but have their obliging Vertue from that Harm. Should They, under pretence of Deſtruction, forbid what Truths were to Edification, They would indeed expoſe the Contraveners to Penalties, but induce no Obligation to Obedience upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. So we ſee the Apoſtles, the great Maſters of Submiſſion and Obedience to Authority, when they were commanded to forbear Preaching the Doctrine of Chriſt, declared plainly, it was their Duty in that caſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer God before Man. But, where Edification requires the Power ſhould be exercis'd, no Power of Man can hinder the Ordinance of God; nor ſhelter thoſe, who do not Evangelize from the <hi>Wo,</hi> with which they are threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As any Biſhop, and any Prieſt might perform the Functions of a Biſhop and Prieſt, in any Part of the World, before Canons were made to limit them to Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Perſons, ſo They may ſtill, where Neceſſity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65377:16"/> or what-ever Circumſtance takes off the Reſtraint, and leaves the Power to its own Original Liberty. Now, the VVords of the Oath ſaying, That no Forreign Prelate has any Spiritual Power in <hi>England,</hi> do, in the utmoſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their Sound, deny, that the properly Spiritual Power, given and commanded to be us'd by Chriſt in all the VVorld, can, even on any occaſion, be exercis'd by any Forreign Prelate in <hi>England.</hi> And this being contrary to the Appointment and Grant of Chriſt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I think, be ſworn by any, who believes in Chriſt: For a Forreign Prelate, being a Prelate, cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Power of a Prelate; nor that Power excluded from any Part of the VVorld, where Edification requires it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I purpoſely abſtain from ſpeaking particularly of the <hi>Pope,</hi> becauſe the Oath ſpeaks not particularly of him; though it comprehends him under the General Term <hi>Prelate;</hi> And becauſe I conceive his Power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us not at preſent, ſince the Caſe would be the ſame, though there were no ſuch thing as a <hi>Pope</hi> in the World. For, our Queſtion is not, What Power forreign Prelates have? but, What they have not? If the Oath be meant, of the Power given by Chriſt, it is oppoſite to the Power given by him to all Prelates, and ſo not Takeable for their ſakes: If it be not meant of that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, it is not oppoſite to what was given by Chriſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and ſo not Refuſable for the <hi>Pope</hi>'s ſake. Our Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, at preſent, is to inquire, What Power the Oath means, not what Chriſt gave. If we find the Oath leaves it untouch't, 'tis beſt for us to leave it ſo too: For to do otherwiſe, is to ſtray into a different and unconcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Queſtion, and amuſe our ſelves unprofitably, with what is not ſpoken of.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65377:16"/>3. That the Oath does not ſpeak of that Power at all, there are many Reaſons to perſwade me. They who fram'd the Oath, were Chriſtians; and knew, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the uncontroulable Power of Chriſt: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagin, they either would go about to take away any thing which he gave, or think they could, though they would. They knew, that notwithſtanding the Confinement of Paſtors to their own Flocks, as firmly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht as Human Laws, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, can eſtabliſh any thing, nothing is more apparent in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory, than that Prelates thought themſelves at liberty to exerciſe the Power of Prelates upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion any where: As <hi>Lucifer,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Calaris</hi> in <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinia,</hi> made them a Biſhop at <hi>Antioch;</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> took care of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and a hundred ſuch Examples there are. <hi>England,</hi> to its great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, has had Experience of the ſame; as when <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Lupus</hi> came hither out of <hi>France,</hi> and preſerved us from <hi>Arianiſm.</hi> At this day, if a Biſhop of the Church of <hi>England</hi> happen to go beyond Sea, as I think ſome did, when His Majeſty was there himſelf; though they carry not with them that External Power, which they have in their own Dioceſes, I ſuppoſe, they do not think themſelves bard from Preaching, or Ordaining, or Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing any Epiſcopal Function, where they think it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or expedient, becauſe they are in the Dioceſs of another Man. And ſo, though the Prieſts, which are Ordained in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are liable in their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Penalty of the Laws in <hi>England,</hi> no Body thinks their Acts invalid. None will Re-baptize one, whom they have Baptized; or think they live in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, who, purſuant to the Doctrine of that Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of Marriage from them. Every For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Perſon is as much excluded by the Oath, as For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65377:17"/> Prelates. Had <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Calvin</hi> come hither, would They have been bard from Preaching or Baptizing by it? Have we not ſeen <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and divers others, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preaching, and Adminiſtring the Sacraments in this Realm? The Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> ordained here, whoſe Ordinations if the Oath rendred invalid, there would be much Confuſion in the Church of <hi>Englond:</hi> For thoſe who were ordained by him, in likelyhood or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained others. Theſe indeed acted with Licence from Authority here: But Power is one thing, Licence to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it another. Licence ſuppoſes, but does not give Power: For, they could not by any Licence be enabled to exerciſe what they had not. How can it be, that Power of this kind ſhould be thought ſpoken of, and meant to be excluded out of <hi>England</hi> by the Oath, which 'tis known, and by the Practice of all ſides con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd, cannot be excluded any where?</p>
               <p n="4">4. But let us conſider the Words themſelves: Every one of the Words, <hi>Power, Juriſdiction, Superiority, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, Authority, Priviledge,</hi> doth in its primary, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and moſt common Acceptation, ſignify ſomething <hi>Human</hi> or <hi>Civil:</hi> I mean, ſo as Power, for example, in its primary, proper, and moſt common Acceptation, ſignifies as much as theſe two Words, <hi>Human Power,</hi> or <hi>Civil Power;</hi> After the manner, that this Word <hi>Man</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies as much as theſe two, <hi>Living-Man,</hi> and the word <hi>Foot,</hi> as much as <hi>Foot of a Living Creature.</hi> In a Secondary, leſs proper and leſs common Senſe, every one of them ſignifies the Power our Saviour gave his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and their Succeſſors, to preach his Doctrine, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade People to practiſe it, and help them to practiſe thoſe Parts of it, (to wit, the Sacraments) which they cannot practiſe without their Help; ſome thing after the manner as the Word <hi>Man</hi> does ſometimes denote a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65377:17"/> 
                  <hi>Picture</hi> or <hi>Statue,</hi> the VVord <hi>Foot,</hi> a <hi>Table-Foot</hi> or <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-Foot.</hi> And the Reaſon of it is, becauſe thoſe Words had the former Senſe before Chriſtianity and the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er belonging to its Preaching and Practice came into the World: and ſo muſt needs be uſed in this Caſe, in a Secondary Senſe: And this, though thoſe VVords were us'd before, concerning other Religions then on foot, from which they might be borrowed, and apply'd to Chriſtianity; becauſe, even at their firſt Application to Religion, they were borrow'd from Families, Cities, or Kingdoms, that were before Religion was ſettled. Next, in the former Senſe it is apply'd to Fathers, in reſpect of their Children; to Houſe-holders, in reſpect of their Families; to all ſorts of Governours of Pariſhes, Towns, Cities, Armies and Kingdoms; and all Officers under them, in reſpect of thoſe they are over; alſo, to the Teachers of all Trades and Arts: But in the later Senſe, to one only Order of Men, or Teachers of one only Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and ſo, more commonly or oftner apply'd to them, than to theſe. Hence, this is alſo the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Senſe, becauſe this is the ſame as the firſt Senſe; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the firſt be moſt commonly us'd.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Again, VVere theſe VVords in a Treatiſe of <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi>-Diſcipline, every <hi>One</hi> would be as much as <hi>Two:</hi> For example, <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> would be as much as <hi>Military Juriſdiction,</hi> and <hi>No Juriſdiction</hi> as much as <hi>No Military-Juriſdiction;</hi> and <hi>No Juriſdiction</hi> in a Book concerning Confeſſion, would without any more ado, be the ſame as <hi>No Juriſdiction to abſolve from Sins:</hi> And for the ſame Reaſon, theſe VVords in a Treatiſe of Civil Matter (as Laws are) ought to be underſtood, ſo that <hi>No Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> be as much as <hi>No Civil Juriſdiction.</hi> Inſomuch, that as it would be ridiculous to think, that <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> in a Military or Confeſſion-Book, means not <hi>Military or Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65377:18"/> Juriſdiction;</hi> ſo it would be abſurd to think, that this VVord <hi>[Juriſdiction]</hi> in a Law-Book, means any thing but <hi>Civil;</hi> except there be ſomething, to determin it to another Senſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Out of this may be ſeen, that every one of theſe VVords, <hi>Power, Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. in the Negative Part of the Oath (which is contain'd in a Law-Book, and is Part of a Law) ought rather to be taken in the former Senſe, then later; So that <hi>No Juriſdiction</hi> be the ſame as theſe three VVords, <hi>No Civil Juriſdiction;</hi> in which Senſe it is evident, that the <hi>Pope</hi>'s, or other Forreign Prelates, not purely <hi>Paſtoral,</hi> or purely Spiritual, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial, and Supernatural Power of the <hi>Keys,</hi> which only regards the Inner-Court of Conſcience; but that Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical (otherwiſe in its own Nature, truly Temporal and Political) Authority in the External Court, which the <hi>Pope</hi> either had or uſurped, or preſcribed or challenged here in <hi>England,</hi> is excluded. I ſay, in caſe there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Oath, or its Acts, to determin them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Senſe: For, if there be nothing to determin them to this later Senſe, then (as I ſaid) they muſt have the former; as the VVords, <hi>No Man at all is at Home,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie no more, than <hi>No Living Man at all is at Home;</hi> except they are by ſome VVord or Circumſtance deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd to ſignifie <hi>No Carv'd or Painted Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That then there is nothing to determin them, is the only thing to be prov'd: And firſt, that the VVords <hi>Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> do not determin them, we have already ſeen; becauſe theſe VVords in Law-Language and Law-Books, where they at preſent were found, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify what is External, Political, and <hi>Civil:</hi> and ſo theſe Words determin them rather to their Law-Senſe, than draw them from it: Eſpecially ſince this <hi>Negative</hi> will not bear a Coherent-Senſe with the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> except <hi>No</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65377:18"/> 
                  <hi>Spiritual Juriſdiction</hi> be the ſame, as <hi>No Civil or Royal Juriſdiction.</hi> For to ſay in the Affirmative, that the Queen hath all Royal Juriſdiction, (or Royal Juriſdiction, in all Cauſes which is the very ſame) and in the Negative, that no Body elſe hath any Royal Juriſdiction, is Coherent Senſe: But to ſay, that ſhe hath all Royal Power of the Sword, and no Body elſe hath any purely Spiritual and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Power of the Keys or Sword; or that ſhe is Queen, and no Body elſe is a Preacher, is very Incoherent and Ridiculous: And yet this muſt be the Senſe, in caſe the Words <hi>No Spiritual Juriſdiction,</hi> be the ſame as <hi>No Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal,</hi> or the ſame as both, <hi>No Royal,</hi> and <hi>No Paſtoral,</hi> as ſome do fancy.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And as the Words <hi>Spiritual, and Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> and the Coherency of Senſe (which we muſt admit, except we be ſuch wiſe Commentators, as to make our Text ſpeak Non-ſenſe) do determin the word <hi>Power,</hi> &amp;c. to ſignify <hi>Royal Power;</hi> ſo doth the whole Deſign aim'd at, as to be brought about by the holding of the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Negative Senſe of the Oath: For this (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the later part of the Oath) is <hi>Faith, and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> to our Prince, and the Defence of the <hi>Juriſdictions of the Crown;</hi> which cannot at all be profeſs'd or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by theſe words, <hi>No Power, Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. as ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to mean any thing elſe, but <hi>No Human Power.</hi> For, if one ſhould deny by them, that our Saviour gave the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other Forreign Prelate, any Power to preach his Doctrine in <hi>England,</hi> how doth this Denial conduce to my Allegiance? Except one ſhould impiouſly ſay, that the Power our Saviour gave to preach his Doctrine, was repugnant to Allegiance, and to the Juriſdictions of any Crown. And hence to ſay, the Makers of the Oath intended, that People by thoſe Words, ſhould deny that Power, is to ſay, they intended People ſhould deny a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65377:19"/> thing, in order to bring about their Allegiance, which hath no order towards the bringing is about: And which they ſaw had none. For, being Chriſtians, they could not think any Power our Saviour gave the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors, (which only is of Faith, and which only we contend they never intended to exclude) was contrary to Allegiance; or, if they thought he gave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch, and yet deny'd it, they left off being Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. What then they apprehended in him, was ſome Power not given by Chriſt, but uſurp'd from our Crown, <hi>hurtful</hi> to it, (as they expreſly ſay;) and this, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this they could deny him, in order to ſecure Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which was their Deſign.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Next, that the word <hi>Prelate</hi> (which is the only remaining Word that hath any ſhew of Difficulty) doth not determin them, appears from this, that the Prelate there intended, (as all ſuppoſe) is one by whom Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Power, as well as Power to Preach, was in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars here uſurped; and, as to the reſt, or all other Branches of it, challenged; and that not only on the pretext of <hi>Divine,</hi> but even of <hi>Human Right, viz.</hi> of the famed Donation or Submiſſion of King <hi>John.</hi> And ſo, the word <hi>Prelate</hi> is ſometimes, by its being apply'd to him, determin'd to Temporal, and ſometimes to Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power. And ſince he is in our Law, and in this Oath, look'd upon as oppoſite to Allegiance, and the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions of our Crown, and ſo rather as a <hi>Prince,</hi> than a <hi>Preacher;</hi> he here determins it to a Temporal Senſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as it is apply'd to him: For, as it is apply'd to all the reſt, as <hi>Prince, Perſon, State,</hi> or <hi>Potentate,</hi> it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently made to ſuppoſe for <hi>Human Power;</hi> and theſe Words being more, it ought, if it have but one Senſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have their Senſe, than the Senſe of <hi>Prelate.</hi> But ſome gueſs, all thoſe other Words are, according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundance
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65377:19"/> of our Law-Language, put to ſignify only one thing; to wit, the <hi>Pope;</hi> who only, (as far as I can learn) had any Power in <hi>England</hi> to be turn'd out, as he is look'd upon in our Law; as Prince, Perſon, State, or Potentate.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The words of the Oath then, do not determin the word <hi>No Power,</hi> to be <hi>No Preaching-Power.</hi> And as for the Acts, who reads them, will find, that there is not ſo much as one word of him, as a <hi>Preacher, Perſwader,</hi> or <hi>Adminiſterer of Sacraments:</hi> And conſequently, not ſo much as one word to determin theſe Words to ſuch a Senſe. But on the contrary, all the Diſcourſe of him, is as of a <hi>Getter of Power</hi> by Sufferance of Princes, and Conſent of People, and Uſurpation from the Crown, in detriment of it: As of a <hi>Uſer of this Power,</hi> in making human, Eccleſiaſtical Laws; as <hi>Judging by thoſe Laws,</hi> in Caſes of <hi>Marriage, Divorces, Wills, Tythes, Oblations, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions;</hi> and as <hi>Diſpenſing in theſe and the like Laws:</hi> In <hi>Getting great</hi> and Intolerable Sums of Money for theſe Diſpenſations: In <hi>Giving</hi> of Benefices, <hi>Receiving</hi> Annats, and Firſt-Fruits: <hi>Giving</hi> Leave to Biſhops, and others, to do their Duties; which needed not, except in caſe of Human Law, they having from Chriſt this Power: and in <hi>Doing</hi> ſuch like Things as theſe. And ſince the Actor of theſe Things, is a Temporal Actor, or an Actor by a Temporal Power, he being conſtantly conſider'd, and ſpoke of in theſe Laws, as an Actor of theſe Things, muſt conſtantly determin the VVords of the ſame Laws, <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. to import <hi>Temporal Power;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently in this Oath, which is made to deny <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>only</hi> that which theſe Acts deny'd him.</p>
               <p n="11">11. In truth, the words <hi>Power, Authority,</hi> and the reſt, have not the ſame Notion, when apply'd to Church-Men, as when they are apply'd to Secular Superiors.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65377:20"/> 
                  <hi>Power</hi> in this caſe, ſignifies Power to <hi>Conſtrain;</hi> in the other, to <hi>Perſwade.</hi> A Biſhop invites a Man to obey him; that is, to Believe, and Live as he from Chriſt inſtructs him, by the Hopes and Aſſurances of the greateſt Goods; and frights him from diſobeying, by the Fears of the greateſt Miſchiefs; which he will certainly bring upon himſelf, who will not be directed by him. If any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Obſtinate, he with-draws from him thoſe Helps to Salvation, which Chriſt has left in the Church, and which his Perverſneſs now renders uſeleſs to him; that by conſidering the Danger of his Caſe, beſides the Shame, and what elſe attends Excommunication, he may be Reclaimed, and <hi>Spiritus ſalvus ſit in die Domini.</hi> Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than this, a Church-Man cannot go, by the Nature of his Power, abſtracting from ſupervening Laws. He cannot take away Meat from the Glutton, nor VVine from the Drunkard, nor lay out the Covetous Man's Money in Alms; nor by Violence, force any Sinner to Virtue. But the Prince, if any Man diſobeys his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, lays hold of him, and by Force conſtrains him to obey. Now, let us conſider, which of theſe two Notions is, in Common Language, generally underſtood by the VVords in queſtion: We do not ſay, a Friend, a Lawyer, a Phyſician, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have Power or Authority; though by not following their Directions, we miſcarry in our Affairs, or loſe our Eſtates, or Health. But a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, a Father, or Maſter, we ſay, have Power over their Subjects, Children, and Servants; becauſe they can force them to do what they command. Plainly therefore, <hi>Power</hi> in Common Language, means <hi>Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Power:</hi> VVhich, if it be ſo, who underſtands the words <hi>Power, Authority,</hi> and the reſt in the Oath, of pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Paſtoral,</hi> or purely Spiritual, or properly <hi>Church-Power</hi> of the Keys, underſtands them otherwiſe, than as they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65377:20"/> properly, and uſually, and alwayes ſignify, unleſs they be determin'd to that leſs proper Signification otherwiſe; which here we have ſeen they are not.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Another evident Argument may be form'd thus; In the Act (1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1.) it is expresſly ſaid, that this <hi>Oath</hi> is made for the Obſervation of that <hi>Act.</hi> Hence there is no more deny'd the <hi>Pope</hi> by this Oath, than by that Act: VVhat is otherways deny'd by the Queen, or her Divines in their Religion, or in Controverſie-Books, being not a Denyal to be acknowledg'd by Oath; elſe it would be to deny all other Things of Faith, in which we differ as well as this, which no Body dreams of. Now, only <hi>Temporal</hi> Power is deny'd by the <hi>Act;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, none but <hi>Temporal</hi> is deny'd by the <hi>Oath:</hi> Only the Second Propoſition wants Proof.</p>
               <p n="13">13. For its firſt Proof, it is ſufficient to read over this Act, and all Acts revived by it, and conſider the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power there ſpoken of; and whether all of it, there ſpoken of, be Temporal: For, if all ſpoken of be Temporal, all deny'd him muſt needs be ſo. The firſt of the Revived Statutes, which taketh any thing from the <hi>Pope,</hi> is in the 24 K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 12. Its Preamble ſpeaks only of ſuch a Power of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as was by reaſon of its Oppoſition to the Prerogatives of the Crown, by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Kings taken from him, and reſtor'd to the Crown. And of ſuch a one as he exercis'd, with great Damage to the Nation, in Cauſes of Appeals in ſeveral Caſes; and for Remedy of this Damage, it is enacted, That he ſhall have this Power, of being a Judge in thoſe Cauſes, no longer. And if it be ſaid, that in this Preamble he is ſpoke of, at leaſt once, as a Preacher, when it is ſaid, that the Clergy of this Realm were alwayes able to Judge of God's Law, without him: I anſwer, This invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates not the Argument; for it is Founded in this, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65377:21"/> where <hi>any</hi> Power is deny'd him, <hi>all</hi> there ſpoken of is Temporal: VVhence is infer'd, that all deny'd him is Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. Now, it is not there ſaid, the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot, or ſhall not Judge what is God's Law, when a Queſtion may riſe in <hi>England</hi> about ſome Point; as a Preacher, or one skillful in God's Law: But that the Clergy is able to do it without him. And thence he ſeems to infer, that 'tis needleſs to appeal out of this Realm, to know of him, what is the Law of God; if there ſhould chance to be any doubt, in caſe of Matrimony or Divorce, for Example: And, it being a needleſs thing to appeal to him even as a Preacher, and inconvenient to appeal to him as a Judge, commands this not to be done. And thus no Power was deny'd him, where he was ſpoke of as a Preacher; but only, where he is ſpoken of as a Judge in thoſe Cauſes, as far as they depend on Human Laws.</p>
               <p>Next, the Statute 25 K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. ſpeaks of no Power taken away, but the Power of exacting Annats, and Firſt-Fruits, and of Electing of Biſhops; which, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving accrew'd to him by time, could not be Divine or Supernatural Power; that is, Power deriv'd to him, or confer'd upon him, <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The Statute (in the 25 K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.) excludes perchance his, as well as our Clergie's Power, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing old Canon-Laws, or making new Ones, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King's Approbation: And the Power of making ſuch Laws, is grounded only on Human Reaſon, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Things preſcribed to be convenient; Of which Conveniency, our Clergy, and alſo Layity, as knowing it beſt by living here, (where a thing may be Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that elſe-where is Convenient) and not the <hi>Pope,</hi> ought to be Judge: VVhich is the Reaſon, why Laws even of General Councils, do not Oblige, except where
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65377:21"/> they are Receiv'd. Hence not ſo much as a Juſt Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Authority is here taken from the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. But if it be here upon this Occaſion, ask'd, VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Clergy and Layity could in Reaſon, and good Conſcience, renounce their Human Power, to continue all ſuch old Canons which the King ſhould not approve of; when as they being more in Number, and more likely to be in the Right than he, might judge either an Old or New Canon convenient, which he might think to be inconvenient? And, hence, whether the King in Reaſon, and good Conſcience could then, and now (by this Act's being Revived, and giving this ſame Power to the King) take, and keep the Power of Repealing all ſuch Canons, as he ſhould pleaſe? And conſequently, whether we can with a good Conſcience, Swear (as we do in the later part of the Oath) to defend this his Power, if Conſcientiouſly poſſeſt by him? I anſwer; That, I believe, they did according to Reaſon and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in rather chooſing the little Harm that might be in the Repealing of ſome good Old Canons, than the great One that might proceed not only from the King's Diſpleaſure, but either from the Continuance of many former bad Canons, or the Enacting of as bad New Ones; or upon ſuch other account, upon which a Man may now, after it is made Law, upon the ſame or a better Motive, continue to conſent to the Continuation of what they did. Likewiſe, the King might as reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably take upon him, that a Law may not be continued, which he diſlikes, as that a Bill, which both Houſes like, may not be a Law, except he likes it; or, as that a Law which he likes, ſhall not be diſcontinu'd, though both Houſes, that are more, diſlike it: And this is for Publick order ſake.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:65377:22"/>17. The Statute (25 K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.) ſpeaks of no Power to be taken away, but Power of diſpenſing in the King's Laws; to the Prejudice of the Crown, and impoveriſhing of the Subjects; which Power muſt be of the ſame Nature, as the Laws diſpenſed with.</p>
               <p n="18">18. The laſt reviv'd Statute, that takes any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, is in the 28 K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. and it takes away on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power of giving Licences in abundance of Human Caſes; and among the reſt, the Power of putting Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops into their Biſhopricks, and Prieſts into their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes; and of giving them leave to do their Divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: VVhich, though it may at firſt Sight, look like Paſtoral Power given him by Chriſt, yet it is not: For, where-ever an Apoſtle dyed, the People and Clergy of the Place had Power to chooſe themſelves a Biſhop; and put him into his Biſhoprick, without the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Conſent. And this Power they Exercis'd for many hundred Years, all over Chriſtendom, according to the Antient Canons and Cuſtoms; till partly, under pretence of Reſpect to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, (but whether truly or only for that Reaſon, is another Queſtion) it was by ſeveral Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates between ſome Emperors, Kings, and Princes, and States of <hi>Europe,</hi> of one ſide, and <hi>Popes</hi> on the other, agreed, There ſhould be no Biſhops allowed in their Territories, but whom the <hi>Pope,</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould approve of. Hence the Power which the <hi>Pope</hi> had, that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop could not, or ſhould not, be put in, without his Conſent, he got by Human Agreement; and only this Power was taken here away. For, it is not ſaid here, that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot, or ſhall not, perſwade People to chuſe themſelves a Biſhop, that he ſees want one; or perſwade a Biſhop, who hath Authority from Chriſt to do it, to go and preach to People that want him, (which may belong to the Care our Saviour gave him over
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65377:22"/> the Church) but that they having a mind to have Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, will have them of their own chooſing, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in; and not of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s, as was of former Times practis'd. And that this is their Senſe, is evident out of the Hiſtory of what the <hi>Pope</hi> did before that time, and of what they themſelves did, and hinder'd him to do afterwards: Or, it may be ſaid, in ſhort, that as they ſaw it not neceſſary by God's Law, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould chooſe and give them a Biſhop, who were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do it themſelves, ſo they thought it not convenient, he ſhould; and thence made a Law, that he ſhould not, The Law not ſaying, that he could not, nor ſhould not, ſend them a Biſhop in caſe of neceſſity, (in which caſe he hath Power from our Saviour, to provide for the Flock; and ſo have other Biſhops too, in ſuch caſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him) but only, that he ſhould not in this caſe of no-Neceſſity: Which is to take from him, not the Power, but the unneceſſary Uſe of that Power; which laſt, was certainly not given by God.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Likewiſe, Biſhops and Prieſts had from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Power to preach, and that all the World over, as they ſhould think fit; without its being neceſſary to have this Power from St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor: But after ſome time, they thought fit to agree, that each one ſhould not do his Duty every where, nor at his own Diſcretion; but only in the Place allotted to him, and at the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion chiefly of the <hi>Pope,</hi> at leaſt, within his Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archate. And the Power, that was by this Agreement given the <hi>Pope,</hi> was here, by the Diſagreement of this Nation in Parliament, taken away: So that now they ſhould have their Places allotted by <hi>it;</hi> and at the Diſcretion of <hi>it,</hi> exerciſe the Power they had from <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:65377:23"/>20. Having thus ſeen, that when any Power of the <hi>Pope</hi> was in the Reviv'd Statutes turn'd out, none but <hi>Human</hi> was ſpoken of: Let us now ſee, of what kind Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſpeaks, in <hi>her</hi> Acts.</p>
               <p n="21">21. In the Title of her Firſt Act, (1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.) none is ſpoken of, but Power <hi>Repugnant to the Antient Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Crown.</hi> Now, one Human Power is often Repugnant to another; and in our Caſe, the <hi>Pope</hi>'s ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Power to <hi>Judge</hi> ſome Cauſes here, without having it, as from or under her, is Repugnant to her Imperial Power, of having all <hi>Judges</hi> in the External-Court, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed under and from her: But not the Miniſterial Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er our Saviour gave to preach his Doctrine, and feed his Sheep; a part whereof, is to render to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s. In the Preamble, we hear only of <hi>Uſurp'd</hi> Power, taken from the <hi>Pope</hi> by K. <hi>H. 8th.</hi> And who can think, that it here calls the Power our Saviour gave to preach, <hi>Uſurp'd?</hi> But, leaſt one ſhould think, they meant not to call the Power which our Saviour gave, Uſurp'd, but to call his pretence of being Chief Preacher, ſo; let him conſider, how the <hi>Antient Juriſdiction of the Crown reſtor'd</hi> is put both here and every where, as relative to it: So that, where-ever there is mention made of Power taken from the <hi>Pope,</hi> there is alſo mention made of Power reſtor'd to the Crown; and where ever of Power reſtor'd to the Crown, alſo of Power taken from the <hi>Pope:</hi> Which gives one reaſon to think, that none was taken away from <hi>Him,</hi> but what was given to the Crown; nor any thing given to the Crown, but what was taken from Him. And this is render'd more evident, by Biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi>'s Words, <hi>Schiſm Garded,</hi> p. 340. <hi>Whatſoever Power our Laws did deveſt the</hi> Pope <hi>of, they inveſted the King with it.</hi> Now, this being ſo, how is it poſſible, they ſhould apprehend the Pretence of being
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65377:23"/> Chief Preacher or Paſtor, though falſe, ſo uſurp'd, as to belong of Antient Time to our Crown, and to be now reſtor'd to it?</p>
               <p n="22">22. Next, by the Fruit, let him know the Tree: And, what is all the Good Fruit there mention'd, as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from what was taken away from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to the Crown? <hi>Being kept in good Order, and freed from intolerable Charges:</hi> which are Temporal Fruits. And, what is all the bad Fruit there mention'd, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the <hi>Pope</hi>'s having got all his Old Power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, by Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Act of Repeal? <hi>Bondage under an Uſurp'd-Forreign Power, to the intolerable Charges of the Subjects.</hi> If this be all the Fruit that grew upon all the Stocks of Power he had formerly taken from him, could any of them be any other, than the Temporal Stock of Power, oppoſit to that by which the King kept them in good Order, or of Power to get Money? And, laſtly, ſince this Preamble deſires nothing but Freedom from theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils; who can imagin, that this Act ſpeaks of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Roots but theſe, to be pluck'd up? Eſpecially, ſince in that Part of the Act, in which this Power is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, it is ſtill all call'd <hi>Uſurp'd,</hi> all call'd <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> Which Words, as being in our Law, muſt determin the word <hi>Power,</hi> to import <hi>Temporal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Laſtly, The Title of the Act, 5 Q. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. being <hi>An Act for the Aſſurance of the Queen's Majeſties Royal Power, over all States and Subjects within her Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions;</hi> the word <hi>Power,</hi> as often as 'tis us'd in the Act, muſt be underſtood in a Senſe conducing to the Aſſurance of <hi>Royal Power;</hi> except one ſhould think the Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers to be ſo Imprudent, as to uſe it in a Senſe no ways conducing to effect their Deſign: and what only Senſe conduces to that end, we have already ſeen. Moreover, the Preamble declaring no Deſign, but the Preſervation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65377:24"/> of the Queen, and the Dignities of her Crown, and the avoyding of Miſchiefs, that have befallen Her, her Crown, and Subjects, by reaſon of the Uſurp'd Power of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> all the VVords of the Act are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of no other Power, than that which is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Cauſe of thoſe Miſchiefs, and of that <hi>only;</hi> which being taken away, the Ends aim'd at will be compaſs'd: and this for the ſame Reaſon alledg'd before. And now, being come to the end of our View of every Particular deny'd by the Acts: And being conſcious, that every particular Power deny'd to the <hi>Pope,</hi> is Temporal; we may ſolidly conclude, that all deny'd him, is ſuch.</p>
               <p n="24">24. For a Second Proof of the ſaid Second Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let us reflect, how it is altogether unreaſonable to think, that theſe Acts take away any Power from the <hi>Pope,</hi> of which they expreſs no diſlike, nor make any Complaint, of its being in him; and how our Eyes teſtify, that they ſignify no diſlike of his Preaching Power: But only of his Power, which was a Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King's Power, as being Part of it, and ſo Repugnant to its being intirely in him; and of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to exact Mony, for Diſpenſations, Licences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was chargeable to the Nation; and which was far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that other, which Chriſt gave him.</p>
               <p n="25">25. For a Third Reaſon, 'tis incredible they would have done a thing in theſe Acts, no wayes conducing to the Deſign they expreſs themſelves to have in them, (which only we ought to judge they had.) For they only ſpeak of reſtoring what was Uſurp'd from the Crown, and aboliſhing what was Repugnant to its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſtor'd; of freeing the Subjects from inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Laws, Judicatures, and great Charges; of ſecuring the Queens Perſon, her Royal Authority over her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and their Allegiance to her. To the compaſſing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65377:24"/> of which End, the taking away the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power to preach Chriſt's Doctrine, (which enjoyns the giving the Crown its due, and is no Power to oppreſs People by Inconvenient Laws, or Exactions of Money in the Caſes complain'd of; nor to prejudice the Queen, or her So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over her Subjects, or their Allegiance to her) is no way conducing: VVhen as the taking the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Temporal Powers away, is very much, as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prov'd.</p>
               <p n="26">26. For a Fourth Reaſon, we may reflect, that this Act, both by its Title and Preamble, ſeems to intend, the Excluſion of only what K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. excluded, in his here approv'd and reviv'd Acts; only with this Difference, that this ſeems to do, at once, and in general VVords, what his did by Parts, and in more particular Terms. And he, as we have ſeen by looking into all Particulars, excluded not the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Paſtor.</hi> More-over, as ſhe did, what he did; ſo he did <hi>fully</hi> what <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings ſhew'd him Example to do. If one may take his VVord in the Preamble to the Statute, 24 King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th. cap.</hi> 12. and the expreſs VVords of his Proviſo, <hi>An.</hi> 25. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. after which he did nothing of Note, beſides ordering that Biſhops ſhould have their Biſhopricks, and preach without the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Order; as they did for a long time among the <hi>Brittains,</hi> and others. Alſo, we may gather their Senſes are the ſame, from alike way of proceeding, and ſpeaking, in Law.</p>
               <p n="27">27. For a Fifth, That 'tis unreaſonable to think, that this Parliament ſhould in this Act exclude the <hi>Pope</hi>'s purely Spiritual Power, as far as it is held to be a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion all over the VVorld; and in the ſame Act, revive the afore-ſaid <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded it ſhould not be excluded: Except we ſhould ſay, that it had at the ſame time, a mind it <hi>ſhould,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:65377:25"/> and <hi>ſhould not</hi> be kept in. <hi>Kept in,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Will</hi> they had, that the Words of the former Statute, ſhould not be taken in a Senſe contrary to the Religion of the then <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, which believ'd Religiouſly, the ſaid purely Spiritual Power of the <hi>Pope,</hi> (which <hi>Will</hi> theſe Men expreſs'd, by Reviving the <hi>Proviſo)</hi> could proceed only from a mind, that no ſuch Religious Tenet, nor conſequently this of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s purely Spiritual Power, ſhould be deny'd: And, <hi>Not kept in,</hi> if in this it denyes or excludes it. And, that the Proviſo commands that, is clear; for it runs thus:</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Provided alwayes, that this Act, nor any Thing or Things therein contained, ſhall be hereafter interpreted, or expounded, that your Grace, your Nobles, and Subjects, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by the ſame to decline, or vary from the Congregation of Christs Church, in any Things concerning the very Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the</hi> Catholick-<hi>Faith of Chriſtendom; or in any other Things declared by Holy Scripture, and the Word of God, neceſſary for Your and Their Salvation: But only to make an Ordinance by Policies, neceſſary and convenient to repreſs Vice, and for good Conſervation of this Realm in Peace, Unity, and Tranquility, from Rapine and Spoyl; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing much the old Antient Cuſtoms of this Realm, in that Behalf: Not minding to ſeek for any Reliefs, Succours, or Remedies, for any Worldly Things, and Human Laws, in any Caſe of Neceſſity within this Realm, but at the Hands of your Highneſs, your Heirs and Succeſſours, Kings of this Realm: which have, and ought to have an Imperial Power and Authority in the ſame; and not oblig'd in any Worldly Cauſes, to any other Superior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29. A Sixth Reaſon is, Becauſe a Proviſo of the laſt Act, 5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. ſayes thus: <hi>Provided alwayes, that for as much as the Queen's Majeſty is otherwiſe ſufficiently aſſur'd of the Faith and Loyalty of the Temporal Lords, of</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:65377:25"/> 
                  <hi>her Highneſſes Court of Parliament: Therefore, this Act, nor any Thing therein contained, ſhall not extend to compel any Temporal Perſon, of or above the Degree of a Baron of this Realm, to take or pronounce the Oath above-ſaid; not to incur any Penalty limited by this Act, for not Taking, or Refuſing the ſame; any thing in this Act, to the contrary, in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> Where we ſee, the Queen's being, without this Act and Oath, ſufficiently aſſur'd of the Temporal Lords <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> is brought as a Reaſon, why neither it, nor its Oath belongs to them; which would have been no Reaſon, in caſe it had been alſo to deny the <hi>Pope</hi>'s being Chief Preacher, (or ſuch a Preacher, as is to have a particular Care, that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> among the reſt, know and practiſe Chriſt's Doctrine; and that all Preachers, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> amongſt the reſt, Preach, and help others under them to Practiſe the ſame.) For the Act and Oath being, in this Suppoſition, made upon two Accounts; to wit, for the Aſſurance of Allegiance, and Denyal of Religion; the Act might have belong'd to them, and the Oath might have been offer'd them, (though the Queen had been other-wiſe aſſur'd or their Allegiance) for Denyal of that Part of Religion, which the Queen was ſo far from being other-wiſe aſſur'd that they did deny, that ſhe otherwiſe certainly knew that, abundance at leaſt of them, did conſtantly profeſs it.</p>
               <p n="30">30. For a Seventh and laſt Reaſon, I alledge, that they could not intend to make People ſwear in the Firſt and Fifth of her Reign, (when this Oath was made and enjoyn'd) that the Pope had not the Power of a Paſtor then in <hi>England;</hi> when as they certainly knew, he had and exerciſed ſuch a Power over Multitudes of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that then were by the State, permitted to Live in, and profeſs an Obedience to him, as ſuch: Eſpecially, if
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65377:26"/> it be found, that the greateſt Part of this Parliament, were <hi>Catholicks;</hi> which would not vote the Forſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Faith. And if they did not intend it, their VVords do not ſignify it. If it be ſaid, they could not intend, to make the People ſwear he had not, <hi>de facto,</hi> ſuch a Power, (ſince every Body knew this to be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Falſe,) but that he had not, <hi>de jure,</hi> or ought not to have ſuch a Power. I anſwer, <hi>1ſt.</hi> That the Words are; <hi>And that no Forreign Prince,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath or ought to have any Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>within this Realm:</hi> And unleſs one will ſay, that <hi>Hath,</hi> and <hi>Ought to have,</hi> are juſt the ſame; and that <hi>Hath</hi> has not its Signification, as well as <hi>Ought to have,</hi> (which is not very likely) the Meaning muſt be, that he hath not, <hi>de facto,</hi> the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they there ſpeak of: Which infers, that they there ſpeak not of Paſtorall Power.</p>
               <p n="31">31. Next, I anſwer, That this Argument evidently concludes, what it endeavour'd; to wit, that they could not intend, that the Words of the Oath ſhould ſignify, that the <hi>Pope</hi> had not any Paſtorall Power in <hi>England, de facto.</hi> And hence, I argue, that they could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take them, in the whole Latitude of their Sound; and alſo, that they intend to exclude no Paſtorall Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>de jure:</hi> Firſt, Becauſe their Words ſpeak no more of this, than they do of that, of which they ſpeak not at all: Next, Becauſe 'tis not likely, that they ſhould intend to make his Paſtorall Power, <hi>de jure,</hi> be abjur'd by ſome, as prejudicial to the Juriſdictions of the Crown, for example; and that others ſhould not abjure it, but be irreprehenſibly permitted to believe, and profeſs it. Laſtly, Becauſe it was <hi>Premunire</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> to hold or profeſs, what the Acts deny'd the <hi>Pope:</hi> But it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prmunire</hi> nor <hi>Treaſon,</hi> for a Lord or other, in thoſe dayes, to profeſs himſelf a <hi>Catholick,</hi> (though it was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65377:26"/> puniſhable, not to be at Common-Prayer) which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the holding and profeſſing the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtorall Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>de jure,</hi> as well as <hi>de facto:</hi> Therefore, it evidently was not this Paſtorall Power <hi>de jure,</hi> that was there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd.</p>
               <p n="32">32. Having thus ſeen, that neither the Words of the Oath, nor the Acts, to the Profeſſion of whoſe Senſe only the Oath is ordain'd, deny the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtorall Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; let us in the laſt Place ſee, whether the Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given it by Act of Parliament, 5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1 denyes it: For, if this doth not, nothing doth that concerns it and us. Now, this Act makes that to be the Senſe of the Oath, which the Queen gives it in her <hi>Admonition:</hi> And ſums up the Senſe of the <hi>Admonition</hi> in ſhort, to be, <hi>To confeſs and acknowledge in her Majeſty, her Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, none other Authority, than that was challeng'd and lately us'd by the Noble King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth, as in the ſaid Admonition more plainly may appear.</hi> Now, ſince the whole Deſign here ſpoken of, (which is to be ſuppos'd <hi>all</hi> of it) is the confeſſing of Power in the Queen, the Negative Part is to be taken to ſignify no farther, than to deny to another, what is confeſs'd to be in the Queen; elſe the whole Buſineſs of the Oath would not be Confeſſing of Power in her: Whence evidently follows, that they are not to be taken in a Senſe, excluſive of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtorall Power. The <hi>Admonition</hi> it ſelf, is as follows.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Admonition</hi> to Simple Men, deceived by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious.</p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>The Queens Majeſty being inform'd that in certain places of the Realm, ſundry of her Native Subjects being call'd to Eccleſiaſtical Miniſtry in the Church, be by ſinister</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65377:27"/> 
                  <hi>Perſwaſion and perverſe Conſtruction, induced to find ſome ſcruple in the form of an Oath, which by an Act of the laſt Parliament is preſcribed to be requir'd of divers Perſons for the Recognition of their</hi> Allegiance <hi>to her Majeſty, which certainly never was ever meant, nor by any Equity of words or good ſenſe can be thereof gather'd; would that all her loving Subjects ſhould understand, that nothing was, is or ſhall be meant or intended by the ſame Oath, to have any other duty,</hi> Allegiance <hi>or bond required by the ſame Oath, than was acknowledged to be due to the moſt noble Kings of famous Memory, K.</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8th. <hi>Her Majeſties Father, or K.</hi> Edward <hi>the</hi> 6th. <hi>Her Majeſties Brother. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, her Majeſty forbiddeth all manner her Subjects, to give ear or credit to ſuch perverſe and malicious perſons, which moſt ſiniſterly and maliciouſly labour to notify to her loving Subjects, how by words of the ſaid Oath, it may be collected that the Kings or Queens of this Realm, Poſſeſſors of the Crown, may challenge Authority and Power of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Divine ſervice in the Church: wherein her ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects be much abuſed, by ſuch evil-diſpoſed perſons; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, her Majeſty neither doth nor ever will challenge any other Authority than that was challeng'd, and lately us'd by the ſaid noble Kings of famous Memory, K.</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8th. <hi>and K.</hi> Edward <hi>the</hi> 6th. <hi>which is, and was of ancient time due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> That is, <hi>under God to have the the Soveraignty and Rule over all manner of perſons born within theſe Realms, Dominions, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, of what estate (either Eccleſiastical or Temporal) ſoever they be,</hi> SO AS, <hi>no other forreign Power ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them. And if any perſon that hath conceived any other ſenſe of the form of the ſaid Oath, ſhall accept the ſame Oath, with this Interpretation, ſenſe or meaning, her Majeſty is well pleaſed, to accept every ſuch in that behalf, as her good and obedient Subjects, and ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65377:27"/> them of all manner of Penalties contain'd in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhall Peremptorily or Obſtinately refuſe to take the ſame Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="34">34. That the <hi>Popes</hi> Paſtoral or purely Spiritual Power is not deny'd in this <hi>Admonition,</hi> may be collected from her ſaying there, that the Oath was requir'd of certain Perſons <hi>for the Recognition of their Allegiance,</hi> and ſuch as was in <hi>Ancient</hi> (and ſo Catholick) <hi>times, due to the Crown.</hi> For the Recognition of which, no Excluſion need or ought to be made of that Power of the <hi>Pope</hi> which is no way <hi>Repugnant</hi> to it, but ſo he uſe his Power as he ought (and if he do not, he is not to be obey'd) a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> of it. Next, from the words, <hi>ſo as no forreign power,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them.</hi> Firſt, becauſe the proper and common (that is, firſt) ſenſe of the words <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Superiority,</hi> is <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi> Next, becauſe <hi>Superiority</hi> is not joynd here to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Prelate,</hi> but as <hi>forreign Power</hi> or <hi>Prince.</hi> And therefore, is by being apply'd to it, determin'd to a <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> ſenſe; and ſo are both of them determin'd to the ſame, by being us'd in an explication of a <hi>Law,</hi> and in in a matter of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> over all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p n="35">35. Laſtly, becauſe the words <hi>SO AS</hi> muſt either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their moſt proper ſenſe, and be an anſwer, to the Great Queſtion that caus'd this <hi>Admonition,</hi> which was, <hi>how</hi> ſhe pretended to be Supream Governour in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Spiritual? whether as a Queen, or as an Adminiſter of divine ſervice in the Church? which therefore, ſeems to be a ſenſe of thoſe words directly belonging to her Purpoſe: And then, 'tis evident that the following words can ſignify only Temporal Authority. For, if it be ask'd <hi>after what manner,</hi> is the Queen Supream Governeſs? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after a Civil or Spiritual manner? and it be anſwer'd,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65377:28"/> 
                  <hi>after ſuch a manner as no forreign power hath or ought to have any Superiority;</hi> (which is the ſame, as if it had been anſwer'd, after a <hi>civil manner;</hi> ſince it was then known to all, that no forreign power had a Superiority after a civil manner, and as certainly known that the <hi>Pope</hi> had one, <hi>de facto,</hi> at leaſt, after a Spiritual manner) It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows out of this Anſwer, that ſhe hath the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, after a <hi>Civil</hi> manner; becauſe, 'tis the ſame thing to ſay, ſhe hath the Supreme Rule after that manner, as no Forreigner hath any; as to ſay, ſhe hath it after a Civil Manner: Of which Truth, ſhe endeavour'd to perſwade ſimple deluded People.</p>
               <p n="36">36. Or the words <hi>SO AS</hi> muſt mean the ſame as <hi>SO THAT.</hi> And then we muſt either ſay the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power is not excluded by the words following; or elſs that no Coherent ſenſe is in them. For in caſe it be excluded, the ſenſe muſt be, The Queen hath the whole Temporal rule over all perſons, ſo that no Forreigner hath power to Preach Chriſt's Doctrine; or ſhe is Queen, ſo that no Forreigner is a Preacher or Paſtor: might not ſhe as pertinently ſay, ſhe is Queen, ſo that no <hi>French</hi> Man is or ought to be a Dancing Maſter? Indeed, if ſhe had taken upon her to have the whole power to Preach, ſhe might have ſaid ſhe is Preacher, ſo that no Forreigner hath, or ought to have any power to preach here; for her having the whole power, hinders any body from having any of it, except under or from her: but not, now, ſhe renounces that: For, the being a Queen, is not at all inconſiſtent with another's being a Preacher. Hence the ſenſe can be no other than either this, <hi>ſhe hath the Rule here, and no body hath any part of it, which is the ſame, as ſhe hath the Rule, and all the Rule:</hi> or elſs this; <hi>ſhe hath all the Rule,</hi> whence it follows, that <hi>no Forreigner hath any part of it, as he pretended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="37">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65377:28"/>37. Laſtly, from the Queens ſaying, that <hi>She will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of thoſe that take the Oath in the above ſaid Senſe, as her good and obedient Subjects;</hi> which ſeems to ſignify, that this Oath was intended, not to know of what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion People were, but to know who were <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient</hi> Subjects; which they may be as well without denying the <hi>Pope</hi>'s preaching Power, as with it. Hence, it is extreamly more probable, at leaſt, that the <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> doth not exclude the Paſtoral Power, than that it doth; and ſo, 'tis a ſufficient Ground for any one to ſay to a Juſtice of Peace, I intend to take this Oath in the Senſe, which to the beſt of my Judgment, is given it by Act of Parliament: Which, as it is ſufficient for the Satisfaction of my Conſcience, (in caſe there be no Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal) for I in my Conſcience, judge, that the King hath the Rule of this Kingdom, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no part of it; and this only I acknowledge upon Oath. Next, I truly ſay, that this Senſe and no other is to the beſt of my Judgment, (though this may poſſibly be miſinform'd) the Senſe given it by Law; and in this, and no other, I take it: So, he can require no more of me, who being to underſtand it, and take it in the Senſe of the Law, do my beſt to do both right. And, more over, agree with almoſt all (as far as I can learn; all) <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Authors, in holding this to be the Senſe of the Law and Oath: And conſequently, am not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd Leave to take it in this Senſe, upon pretence that the Senſe I take it in, is not allowable, ſince 'tis allow'd Publickly.</p>
               <p n="38">38. Since then (as we ſhall find, if we reflect back upon the whole) the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtoral Power, if excluded, muſt be excluded, by not taking the Words of the Oath in their moſt <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Proper</hi> Senſe; to which alſo they are determin'd by being in Law-Books, by all <hi>other</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65377:29"/> words of the Oath, by its Deſign, and the words of all Acts concerning it: Since it muſt be excluded by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without being ſpoke of; ſince it muſt be excluded by Reaſon of ſome diſlike, without expreſſing that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; when as it is the Cuſtom of theſe Laws, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Reaſon that mov'd the Parliament to do what it did: Since it muſt be excluded by the Parliament's doing a thing, even in their own Thoughts, nothing conducing to the End they deſign'd; <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>Allegiance, Freedom from Charges,</hi> &amp;c. which a Power purely Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual in the <hi>Pope</hi> no way prejudices: Since it muſt be excluded by following the Example of <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings, as to manner of Proceeding, Words, Things, and All, except ſome few Particulars; which look'd into, ſeem no more to exclude his Paſtorſhip, than what they did: Since it cannot be excluded without the Parliament's <hi>willing,</hi> that like Words of a former Act, ſhould not be taken in a Senſe excluſive of it; which could proceed only from a Will to have it not-excluded: And <hi>willing</hi> at the ſame time, that the Words of this Act be taken in a Senſe excluſive of it; which could proceed only from a Will to have it excluded: Since it cannot be excluded without their bringing a Reaſon for the Lords not taking of it, which was no Reaſon; without having a mind to ſwear, that the <hi>Pope</hi> had <hi>not,</hi> what they cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſaw he <hi>had;</hi> or, at leaſt, to ſwear he had not a Power, in words that did not ſignify the Excluſion of it, more than of that they did not exclude: Since it could not be excluded, except it was Treaſon to profeſs what was excluded, and not Treaſon to profeſs what was excluded; (ſince if it be ſuppos'd, that the <hi>Pope</hi>'s properly Paſtoral Power was excluded, it was Treaſon according to the Act, to profeſs it; and otherwiſe, we know it was not Treaſon to profeſs it; all <hi>Catholicks</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65377:29"/> not then eſteem'd and puniſh'd as Traitors): Since it could not be excluded, except the Negative Clauſe be put ſo, as not to conduce at all to bring about the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſigne of the Oath; which was acknowledging Power in the Queen, profeſſing Allegiance, and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of who were good Subjects: Nor except the words of the Admonition be taken improperly, and the later part of it be conſtru'd into Non-ſenſe. Since theſe Things are ſo, as likewiſe, that almoſt all Words (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if not conſider'd in their proper Circumſtances, as theſe uſe not to be, but as they ly in a ſingle Paper, ſeparated from all that belongs to them) are liable to have a wrong Senſe forc'd into them; 'tis, I think, as evident as any thing of this Nature can well be; that this which I have endeavour'd to prove to be the Senſe of the Oath, is indeed the true Senſe of it: And ſo, as evident, (when theſe Things are publickly known) as we need deſire for our Swearing, that the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power (as of Faith) is not excluded nor abjur'd, what ever may be ſaid of his other Powers, that were in proceſs of Time added to this. Neither am I alone, in this Thought: <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Divines, of the greateſt Note, and very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law, (which alone ſeems able to give ſolid Satisfaction in this Point) bear me company, or rather, I bear them. They may be ſeen at large cited by Mr. <hi>Creſſy,</hi> in his Reflexions upon the Oaths, <hi>pag.</hi> 27. to 33. and in the <hi>Seaſonable Diſcourſe</hi> about the Oaths of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> very lately Printed, from <hi>p.</hi> 27. to <hi>p.</hi> 32. The Sum of their Senſe is this, That they clear both the Affirmative and Negative Clauſe in the Oath, from intending either to exclude the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtoral, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural, purely Spiritual, or Miniſterial Power of the Keys, or to give (as I have ſhewn) any ſuch Power to the King; and this in as expreſs Words, as can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65377:30"/> Which, leſt this Treatiſe ſhould be any way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, I ſhall here repeat.</p>
               <p n="39">39. In Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reign, we have the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Of Subject. 2. <hi>Par. p.</hi> 218.</note> of Doctor <hi>Bilſon,</hi> afterwards Biſhop, of <hi>Winchester,</hi> whoſe expreſſions are theſe; <hi>The Oath</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not the duty of Princes to God, but ours to them. And as they muſt be obey'd when they joyn with the Truth, ſo muſt they be endured when they fall into errour. Which ſide ſoever they take, either obedience to their Wills, or ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to their ſwords, is their due by Gods Law. And that is all which our Oath exacteth.</hi> Again, <hi>This is the ſupreme power of Princes, which we ſoberly teach, and which you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. ibid,</hi> p. 256.</note> [JESUITS] <hi>ſo bitterly deteſt, That Princes be Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in their own Dominions; bearing the Sword, freely to permit, and publickly to defend that which God commandeth in Faith and good Manners; and in Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline to receive and eſtabliſh ſuch Rules and Orders, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Canons ſhall decide to be needful and healthful for the Church of God in their Kingdoms. And as they may lawfully command that which is Good in all Things and Cauſes, be they Temporal, Spiritual, or Eccleſiaſtical: So may they with juſt Force remove whatſoever is Erroneous, Viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or Superſtitious within their Lands, and with External Loſſes and Corporal Pains repreſs the Broachers and Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of Hereſies, and all Impieties. From which Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto Princes, no Man within their Realms, Monk, Prieſt, Preacher, nor Prelate is exempted. And without their Realms no Mortal Man hath any Power from Chriſt, judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to depoſe them, much leſs to invade them in open Field; least of all, to warrant their Subjects to rebel against them.</hi> Moreover, intending to explain in what ſenſe Spiritual <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 173. in marg.</note> Juriſdiction ſeems by the Oath to be given to Princes, he ſaith firſt: <hi>We make no Prince Judge of Faith.</hi> And <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid,</hi> p. 252.</note> then more particularly: <hi>To deviſe new Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65377:30"/> for the Church is not the Princes Vocation: But to receive and allow ſuch as the Scriptures and Canons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and ſuch as the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Place ſhall adviſe, not infringing the Scriptures or Canons. And ſo, for all other Eccleſiaſtical Things and Cauſes, Princes be neither the Deviſers nor Directers of them; but the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmers and Eſtabliſhers of that which is Good, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placers and Revengers of that which is Evil. Which Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, we ſay, they have in all Things and Cauſes, be they Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, Eccleſiaſtical, or Temporal.</hi> Hereto his Adverſary is brought in replying; <hi>And what for Excommunications and Abſolutions, be they in the Princes Power alſo?</hi> To this he anſwers; <hi>The Abuſe of Excommunication in the Prieſt, and Contempt of it in the People, Princes may puniſh: Excommunicate they may not, for ſo much as the Keys are no part of their Charge.</hi> Laſtly, to explain the Negative Clauſe in the Oath, he ſayes; <hi>In this ſenſe we defend</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 218.</note> 
                  <hi>Princes to be Supreme, that is not at liberty to do what they liſt, without regard of Truth or Right: But without Superior on Earth to repreſs them with violent Means, and to take their Kingdoms from them.</hi> Thus Doctor <hi>Bilſon;</hi> whoſe Teſtimony may be interpreted to be the Queens own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Oath; ſince, as appears by the Title page of his Book, what he wrote <hi>was peruſed and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Publick Authority.</hi> And to ſuch a Senſe of the Oath as this, there is not a Catholick Clergy Man in <hi>France, Germany, Venice,</hi> or <hi>Flanders, but would reatdly ſubſcribe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="40">40. In the next place, ſuitable to him, Doctor <hi>Carle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in King <hi>James</hi> his time, thus ſtates the Matter: <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>diſputing of Juriſdiction, ſaith, There</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Carleton of <hi>Juriſdict.</hi> c. 1. p. 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>is a Triple Power in the Biſhop of</hi> Rome: <hi>Firſt, of Order; ſecondly, of Internal Juriſdiction; Thirdly, of External Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. The Firſt is refer'd to the Sacraments; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65377:31"/> to Inward Government, which is in the Court of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; the Third to that External Government, which is practiſed in External Courts. And confeſſeth, that of the Firſt and Second there is no queſtion between us, but only of the Third. Then of this</hi> (ſaith <hi>Carleton) we are agreed, that the Queſtion between us and them, is only of Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on coactive in External Courts, binding and compelling by Force of Law, and other External Mulcts and Puniſhments, beſides Excommunication. As for Spiritual Juriſdiction of the Church ſtanding in examination of Controverſies of Faith, judging of Hereſies, depoſing of Hereticks, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of notorious Offenders, Ordination of Prieſts and Deacons, Inſtitution and Collation of Benefices and Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Cures,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>this we reſerve intire to the Church, which Princes cannot give or take from the Church. This Power hath been practiſed by the Church, without Coactive Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, other than of Excommunication. But when Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters handled in the Eccleſiaſtical Conſiſtory, are not Matters of Faith and Religion, but of a Civil Nature; which yet are called Eccleſiaſtical, as being given by Princes, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be within the Cogniſance of that Conſiſtory: And, when the Cenſures are not Spiritual, but Carnal, Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, Coactive; here appeareth the Power of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. This Power we yield to the Magiſtrate; and here is the Queſtion, Whether the Magiſtrate hath right to this Power or Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>This then is the thing that we are to prove, That Eccleſiaſtical coactive Power, by force of Law and corporal Puniſhments, by which Chriſtian People are to be governed in external and contentious Courts, is a Power which of right belongeth to Chriſtian Princes.</hi> Again, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. ibid.</hi> p. 42.</note> afterward he ſayes; <hi>Concerning the Extention of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Juriſdiction, it cannot be denyed, but that there is a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Church, not only Internal, but alſo of External Juriſdiction. Of Internal Power there is no queſtion made.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65377:31"/> External Juriſdiction, being underſtood all that is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in External Courts, or Conſiſtories, is either Definitive or Mulctative. Authority Definitive in Matters of Faith and Religion, belongeth to the Church. Mulctative Power may be understood either as it is with Coaction, or as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Spiritual Cenſures. As it ſtandeth in Spiritual Cenſures, it is the right of the Church, and was practiſed by the Church, when the Church was without a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and ſince. But Coactive Juriſdiction was never practiſed by the Church, when the Church was without Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates: But was alwayes understood to belong to the Civil Magistrate, whether he were Chriſtian or Heathen.</hi> After this manner doth Doctor <hi>Carleton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> underſtand the <hi>Supremacy of the King,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the Oath.</p>
               <p n="41">41. In the laſt place, Doctor <hi>Bramhal,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in our late King's dayes, and now Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> thus declares both the <hi>Affirmative</hi> and <hi>Negative</hi> Parts of the Oath, touching the King's Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in matters Eccleſiaſtical, and renouncing the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <note place="margin">Schiſme guarded.</note> Juriſdiction in the ſame, here in <hi>England,</hi> in his Book called <hi>Schiſm Guarded,</hi> &amp;c. The ſum of which Book is in the Title-page expreſt to conſiſt in ſhewing, <hi>That the great Controverſie about Papal Power, is not a queſtion of Faith, but of Interest and Profit; not with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>but with the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Judicious Writer, thus at once ſtates the Point in both theſe Reſpects. <hi>My last Ground</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>is, That neither King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, nor any of his Legiſlators, did ever endeavour to deprive the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>of the Power of the Keys, or any part thereof; either the Key of Order, or the Key of Juriſdiction: I mean, Juriſdiction purely Spiritual, which hath place only in the inner Court of Conſcience, and over ſuch Perſons, as ſubmit willingly. Nor</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:65377:32"/> 
                  <hi>did ever challenge or endeavour to aſſume to themſelves ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Key of Order, or the Key of Juriſdiction purely Spiritual. All which they deprived the</hi> Pope <hi>of, all which they aſſumed to themſelves, was the External Regiment of the Church by Coactive Power, to be exerciſed by Perſons ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the Reſpective Branches of it. This Power the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>never had, or could have juſtly over their Subjects, but under them whoſe Subjects they were. And therefore, when we meet with theſe Words, or the like, (That no Forreign Prelate ſhall exerciſe any manner of Power, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical with this Realm) it is not to be underſtood of Internal, or purely-Spiritual Power in the Court of Conſcience, or the Power of the Keys, (we ſee the contrary practiſed every day) but of External and Coactive Power in Eccleſiastical Cauſes, in</hi> Foro contentioſo. <hi>And, that it is, and ought to be ſo underſtood, I prove clearly by a Proviſo in one main Act of Parliament, and an Article of the Engliſh Church.</hi> [Which Act and Article have been produced above.] The Biſhop continues: <hi>They (that is, the Parliament) profeſs, their Ordinance is meerly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical: What hath a Political Ordinance with Power purely Spiritual? They ſeek only to preſerve the Kingdom from Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,</hi> &amp;c. And then having produced the Article, he concludes: <hi>You ſee the Power is Political, the Sword is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical, all is Political. Our Kings leave the Power of the Keys and Juriſdiction purely Spiritual, to thoſe to whom Chriſt hath left it.</hi> Nothing can be more expreſs, than this ſo clear a Teſtimony of ſo Judicious a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> touching the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Supremacy,</hi> in matters Eccleſiaſtical, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Oath.</p>
               <p n="42">42. Again, the ſame <hi>Biſhop</hi> thus further adds: <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 169.</note> 
                  <hi>our Laws do deny all Spiritual Juriſdiction to the</hi> Pope <hi>in</hi> England, <hi>it is in that Senſe that we call the Exterior Court of the Church, the Spiritual Court. They do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65377:32"/> at all to deprive him of the Power of the Keys, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spiritual Power that was bequeathed him by Chriſt, or by his Apostles, when he is able to prove his Legacy.</hi> To conclude, omitting a World of other Paſſages to the ſame effect, he ſaith; <hi>We have not renounced the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 219.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Papacy, except the Subſtance of the Papacy do conſist in Coactive Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="43">43. And that we may ſee this ſtill continues the Senſe of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church (and conſequently of the State) even to this day, Mr. <hi>Falkner</hi> of <hi>Lynn Regis,</hi> in his Book entituled, <hi>Chriſtian Loyalty,</hi> ſo lately Printed, that it was Antedated 1679, and dedicated to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Page 200. gives us the Senſe of this Oath in theſe Words: <hi>This Oath tending, according to the Deſigne of that Statute by which it was Eſtabliſh't, to reſtore to the Crown its Antient Juriſdiction, that Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is chiefly rejected thereby, is ſuch as invaded or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Royalty of the King; and particularly, that which claimeth any Supreme Cognizance of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as if they were not under the Care of the Temporal Power, or that pretendeth to any other Authority above and against the Just Rights of the Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="44">44. Now, that ſuch Authors, (eſpecially the Three firſt) ſo Univerſally read by all Learned-Men in their reſpective Times, and (doubtleſs) amongſt others by Thouſands learned in the Law, ſhould paſs without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the leaſt Reprehenſion for interpreting the Oath and our Laws wrong, in caſe they had, in ſuch their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Expoſitions, declin'd from the true Senſe of the Lawgivers; nor be diſcountenanc't by thoſe reſpective Princes, as diminiſhing the Extent of their Power, or by the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church and State; for reſerving more to the <hi>Pope</hi> than was meant by them, when they requir'd <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to take the Oath; but, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that their Works ſhould paſs without the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65377:33"/> and Cenſure; nay, be Univerſally receiv'd with the higheſt Eſteem and Applauſe; and that their Perſons ſhould be ſo Careſſed and Advanc'd by thoſe Princes, is a Riddle paſt mine or any man's Solving. Princes and States uſe not to be ſo ſupine in ſuch Matters, as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a wrong Senſe to be impos'd upon their Laws; leaſt of all, thoſe who are not in Communion with <hi>Rome;</hi> eſpecially, when their own and the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Authority are concern'd: And yet, we muſt either ſay, that ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in ſuch Matters, were thus ſtrangely negligent; or elſe be forc't to acknowledge, that in the Senſe of all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Lawyers there, and even of our Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that was the True and Legal Senſe of the Oath of Supremacy, which thoſe eminent Authors aſſign'd and declar'd. This Argument will have far greater Force, if we add, that not one <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Author amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that have either written expreſly, or touch't upon that Subject, was ever found, who contradicted this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theirs, or affirm'd any Power <hi>purely Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,</hi> to be given the King, or taken from the Pope by this Oath: Which, the Fancies of Mankind, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe of many ſeveral Judgments in other things, and all of them averſe to the Pope) and the Opinions of Writers, being naturally ſo various, evidences that this Sentiment of theirs concerning the aboveſaid Meaning of the Oath, was not only <hi>Univerſally,</hi> but moreover <hi>Firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and conſtantly held as an undoubted Truth. And let it be noted here, that all theſe four Learned Authors ſpeak of the Oath, both as to the Affirmative and Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Clauſe in it; that is, both of what they attribute by it to the King, and deny by it to the Pope. Out of which Diſcourſe it follows, that though theſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies taken ſingly, do not amount to a Publick Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Senſe of the Oath; yet taking them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyntly,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65377:33"/> with all their reſpective Qualifications and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, they evidently argue, that the Senſe they and we affix to the Oath, is agreed to by all ſorts of intelligent People in <hi>England,</hi> to be indeed the True Senſe of it: Which Univerſal Conſent ſeems equivalent to any Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declaration whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Section III. <hi>Objections Anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding the Evidence of what we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd above, mens Fancies, Intereſts and Humours being various, there remain diverſe Scruples in the minds of many, and I will endeavour to eaſe them of thoſe that have come to my knowledge, and ſeem any way Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, 'Tis Objected that the words of the Oath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all manner of <hi>Power</hi> to the Pope. But how could they do otherwiſe? Had they gone about to have num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd all the particulars which they intended to Aboliſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that 'twould have been extreamly tedious (in an Oath eſpecially), ſome perhaps would have eſcaped their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt diligence. Had they excluded <hi>Ordinary</hi> Power, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> or <hi>Delegate</hi> might ſtill have pretended. The Aboliſhing the <hi>Legantine,</hi> might have left that <hi>Ex pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine Poteſtatis; Annates</hi> had not taken away Appeals;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65377:34"/> nor Appeals, Habilitating to Inheritances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor they Expectatives, nor Reſervatives, nor <hi>Non Obſtantes,</hi> &amp;c. Had they gone that way to work, whatſoever had not been expreſly named, would have been underſtood not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; and then a new Law or a new Oath muſt have been made for that; and then another might have been found out, and no end have ever been. Wherefore, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs what they intended, it was neceſſary to uſe a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Expreſſion; which they knew was to be underſtood as all Rules of Law and Language require it ſhould, of the matter in hand: ſo that <hi>[No Power]</hi> here imports as much as <hi>no Civil Power,</hi> no Power repugnant to the Kings <hi>Governing Power in all Cauſes,</hi> no ſuch power as Queen Elizabeth and her Anceſtor-Princes had of old in this Realm, as was largely ſhown above. And hence, to take the Oath right, one ought to think not of the ſingle words taken in their whole Latitude as deveſted of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, but as taken in Complexion with them; it being but a very Odd Scrupuloſity to think the Oath is to be taken in ſuch a manner as if one did not live in the world, nor knew any thing of it's Circumſtances; but were to lay aſide all knowledges he had gain'd all his life, except onely of the ſignification of thoſe very Words, abſtracting from all Subjects of which they may be conceiv'd to ſpeak; which amounts in other Terms to this, that, while they take the Oath, they muſt lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all uſe of common ſenſe; nay, and ſwear too they know not what: for, laying aſide the knowledge of all Circumſtances, every word in the world is ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis objected, Secondly, that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which may be preſumed to underſtand this Oath beſt, ſays in the latter part of the 37th Article, in which it ſeems to relate to the Negative part of this Oath, that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65377:34"/> 
                  <hi>the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>hath no Juriſdiction in this Realm of</hi> England. 'Tis anſwered, the proper and primary ſenſe of the word <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> is the Powers of a Magiſtrate giving Sentence according to Right or Law, with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in External Courts, to make it be Executed; from whence in a ſecundary ſignification, 'tis transferr'd to the inward Court of Conſcience. But it carries it's notion in it's Terms: <hi>Dictio Juris,</hi> or <hi>Jus dicere</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in it's firſt, and obvious ſenſe to determin with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which may force Obedience to what is Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. This it ſeems, is all which the Church of <hi>England</hi> underſtands deny'd to the <hi>Pope</hi> by the Oath, which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Charleton</hi> cited above, in terms acknowledges, by ſaying, that <hi>There is no queſtion between us, concerning</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Carleton <hi>Of Juriſdiction,</hi> c. 1. p. 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the Internal Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome; <hi>but only the External:</hi> And this plainly relates to the Judiciary Power ſpoken of. Eſpecially, ſince the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> here ſpeaks of <hi>No Juriſdiction</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after ſhe had ſpoke what was due to the King; and conſequently, in the ſame Senſe here, as ſhe did there; that ſo, by ſaying the <hi>Pope</hi> had <hi>No Civil Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> ſhe might ſignify, that the King had not only Civil Power, but alſo <hi>all of it,</hi> ſince the <hi>Pope</hi> hath now <hi>none,</hi> who had <hi>ſome</hi> formerly; elſe we muſt come to the before-noted Inconſequent way of ſpeaking, <hi>He is King here, and the</hi> Pope <hi>is not a Preacher or Paſtor here.</hi> That I may not omit, that ſhe ſpeaks here in reference to our Laws, which ſpeak of Juriſdiction in this Senſe only, and which took from the <hi>Pope</hi> only this kind of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And this is fully and clearly affirmed by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Dr. <hi>Bramhal, Schiſm Garded,</hi> p. 308. as above cited. And again, <hi>p.</hi> 340. <hi>Our Laws do not intend at all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the</hi> Pope <hi>of the Power of the Keys—in relation to</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:65377:35"/> England <hi>it ſelf: Our Parliaments did never pretend to any Power, to change or abridge Divine Right,</hi> &amp;c.—for the VVhole is too long to be Tranſcrib'd, and yet 'tis fit it ſhould be read. Again, p. 337. <hi>Our Anceſtors cast out External Coactive Juriſdiction; the ſame do we. They did not take away from the</hi> Pope <hi>the Power of the Keys, or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction purely Spiritual; No more do we.</hi> We have a ſecond, or at leaſt a Confirmation of this Anſwer, in <hi>Franciſcus a S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Clara</hi>'s Paraphraſtical Explication of the 39. Articles of the Church of <hi>England, pag.</hi> 412. where he ſayes on the above-ſaid Negative Paſſage of the 37. Articles, That, peradventure, it meant only to deny <hi>England</hi> to be held in Fee from the <hi>Pope,</hi> by virtue of King <hi>John</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Submiſſion to, and Reception of his Crown again, from <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and his Promiſe of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribute to the <hi>Pope</hi> for it. This vain, ridiculous, empty Title, (as Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> himſelf called it, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anem Titulum)</hi> was that peradventure, ſayes the fore-ſaid <hi>à S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Clara,</hi> which that Negative Paſſage of the 37. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle rejected. For the Lawful Rejection of which, he brings Proofs ſufficiently convincing in the Page now quoted. But whether or no he gheſſes aright at the Meaning of that Paſſage, it matters not much; ſince the Objection has been otherwiſe already and ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Third Objection proceeds from King <hi>James</hi>'s ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the Oath of Supremacy <hi>was deviſed for putting a Difference between</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and them of our Profeſſion:</hi> And Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> that the Oath of Supremacy was made <hi>to diſcover thoſe who acknowledg'd the</hi> Pope's <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and deny the King</hi>'s. Whence it ſeems to follow, that what ever Senſe this Oath might have had in Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Dayes, yet King <hi>James</hi> gave it another, oppoſite to a Tenet held generally by <hi>Catholicks;</hi> elſe how could
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65377:35"/> it diſtinguiſh them, in caſe there was no Senſe oppoſit to ſuch a Tenet? For in this caſe, they might take it as well as the reſt, and not be diſtinguiſhed from them by taking it. And the Senſe K. <hi>James</hi> gave it, <hi>ſeems to</hi> continue ſtill, ſince no Body ſince ever took it out of the Oath. I anſwer, It doth not follow: For in Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that neither Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> gave it that Senſe, nor K. <hi>James,</hi> nor he ſo much as apprehended it to be given by her; yet, ſince he ſaw, that all <hi>Catholicks</hi> did appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it in a Senſe oppoſit either to ſome Religious Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of theirs, or at leaſt, ſome other Poſition, which they judg'd True; and upon that account did as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly refuſe it, as if it had really deny'd ſuch a Tenet or Poſition; he might if he pleas'd, make uſe of their Refuſal, as a way (though <hi>needleſs,</hi> as Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> obſerves) to know they were <hi>Catholicks.</hi> And as this Argument doth not prove, that he did give it a New Senſe, different from what Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> gave it; ſo 'tis evident, he did not. For, that Senſe muſt have been either oppoſit to the Queen's, and this he did not give it, ſince he let the Queen's Act remain unrepeal'd; by which it neceſſarily retain'd her Senſe, with which its Oppoſit could not be: for a Senſe excluſive of Paſtoral Power, muſt have been ſuperadded to the former Senſe; and this he alſo did not; Firſt, becauſe, ſince he takes not that Power to himſelf, the Words will not with good Senſe, bear the Excluſion of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power: Next, becauſe he in his Apology for the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>pag.</hi> 46. declares himſelf not to be againſt this Power of the <hi>Pope;</hi> ſaying, That he could be content, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> were Patriarch of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and were the Firſt among all Biſhops, and <hi>Princeps Epiſcoporum,</hi> ſo as he be no otherwiſe, than as <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>Princeps Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum;</hi> which is all we contend for; and who can
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65377:36"/> think, that he put a Senſe into an Oath, to make Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forſwear, what he himſelf did not diſlike?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, becauſe this could not have been done by him, ſo at leaſt, as to oblige <hi>Catholicks,</hi> by reaſon of its being in, not to take the Oath, in caſe it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe lawful; except he had declar'd by Law, or at leaſt, by ſome Authentick Act, ſuch a Senſe to be new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put into it: For, in caſe they had not known of it, it would have been all one to them, as if it had not been in at all: And how ſhould they know of it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it had been ſome ſuch way made known to them? Neither will an accidental and ambiguous Sentence in a Book, be, in the Judgment of any wiſe Man, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Declaration of his Mind. Moreover, the Caſe ſeems to be this; He did not doubt, but that a great many of his <hi>Catholick</hi> Subjects were Loyal; but did doubt, ſome were not: And had a mind to know, who was of the former, and who of the later Sort; but could not by the tendering the former Oath, which both Sorts refus'd. Hence he, out of Kindneſs to the Loyal, made another Oath, which he thought Theſe would, and Thoſe would not take. And this is all the apparent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his former Aſſertion; except He, or Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> might be of the general Opinion of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that, that Oath was begun and continued, with deſign to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them from <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> For, beſides this, to think, as ſome Speculators ſeem to do, that K. <hi>James</hi> deſign'd the very Action of taking the Oath, though the Senſe of it were held True by <hi>Catholicks,</hi> to be a new Sign, to ſignify as much as theſe Words, <hi>I am no Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> without either Law or other Declaration, is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit as odd, as 'tis groundleſs. Beſides that, theſe Words writ by Chance, as it were, ſhould have ſo much weight put in them, ſeem to me ſo unreaſonable, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65377:36"/> I think it very reaſonable to be of the contrary Opinion. But the Truth is, there is a grand Miſtake in the Ground of this Objection, and theſe Authors are indeed miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented; for neither of them ſay, that the Oath of Supremacy was <hi>intended at first,</hi> when it was made in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Dayes, to diſtinguiſh <hi>Catholicks</hi> from <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> nor can it with any Senſe be ſo thought, as has been ſhewn above. And as for King <hi>James,</hi> his Words are theſe; As for the Oath of <hi>Supremacy, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the CONTINUATION of it, was to the end to diſcover who were</hi> Roman-Catholicks, <hi>and who</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. With which words it may very well conſiſt, that ſince <hi>Catholicks,</hi> ſome out of Ignorance, others out of intereſt or bad Principles, had Univerſally refus'd it, and ſo, had made themſelves liable to diſcovery, by not taking it; he, like a wiſe and politick Prince, made uſe of their Refuſing him that juſt Duty, by <hi>continuing</hi> the ſaid Oath, ſo to diſcover them, without any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that he ſhould either impoſe a new Senſe on it, or declare, that the Original Senſe was indeed oppoſit to <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, or a Signe really diſtinguiſhing them from <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by any Act or Intention of the State; but only by their own private Opinion, that the Oath claſh't with their Faith.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Fourth Objection is grounded upon this, That Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who made the Oath, made ſeveral Laws to deſtroy the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, by hindering any Prieſt by Authority of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> to Preach it here, and ſo to aboliſh his Paſtoral Authority; which ſeems to argue, that in her Oath ſhe alſo deny'd it; and upon this, that <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who endeavour to have the ſame Faith deſtroy'd, may now give this Oath a New Senſe, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to bring about that end; and in this Senſe, which we cannot deny, offer it us now. But I deny the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65377:37"/> Conſequence; becauſe, 'tis moſt likely, that ſhe deny'd nothing by this Oath, but what is deny'd by it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in the Senſe of the before mention'd Acts, and her Admonition; which laſt aſſures us, that who ever takes it in that Senſe, ſhall be eſteem'd her good and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Subjects, and freed from all the Penalties of that Act; which is all we need aim at. And all She aim'd at by the Oath, was (as we have ſeen) to know, who were to be eſteem'd her good and obedient Subjects: And not to deſtroy by it, that Article of our Faith, equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Allegiance, as the reſt; which it is certain, ſhe did not intend to deſtroy, by that Oath; though by other Means, ſhe might then, or rather afterwards, (for it was long after that, ſhe made thoſe ſevere Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith) intend to deſtroy, not only that, but alſo all other Articles of our Faith, which were oppoſit to hers; that ſo ſhe might make the State-Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion encreaſe, and not that ſhe might know who were her good Subjects. Moreover, 'tis unlikely, that ſhe ſhould give an Oath, which ſhe explicated in any other Senſe, than that in which ſhe explicated it by Law; ſince the giving it in that other Senſe, could proceed from no other Deſign, than of having that other Senſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd by the Taker; which he could not, in our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition deny, becauſe he knew nothing of it. And hence, my Opinion is, that her only Deſign, was not to have any Tenet of Catholick Religion, Doctrine, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion deny'd; but to know, who would be True to her, againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Queen of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Moreover, 'tis evident, that Information given of a Horrid Treaſon, caus'd our good King to enjoyn its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken now.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But though it be ſuppoſed, that we are out in theſe Speculations, and that the Queen afterwards had a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65377:37"/> deſign, to make ſome Tenet of Catholick Religion be deny'd by it, (and the ſame be ſaid at preſent) yet ſhe us'd an Inſtrument, that was inefficacious, to bring about that Effect; except a Senſe oppoſit to Catholick Religion or Doctrine, had been ſo put into it, that a Catholick might have been obliged to take it in that Senſe: For, if he be ſtill at Liberty to take it only in a True Senſe, and doth this, he denies not his Religion. Now, that a Catholick was and is ſtill at Liberty to take it only in that true Senſe given it by Law, is evident; becauſe, if he will take it in that, and will not take it in any other, he is freed from all Penalties that may force him to take it. Add, that the Queen's Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being allow'd by a Statute-Law, made in the Fifth of her Reign; the Allowance to take it in that Senſe, cannot Legally be deny'd any.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A Fifth Objection ariſes from our ſwearing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all Juriſdictions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> annexed to the Crown; among which is the Power to execute Laws, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what we hold to be Chriſt's Doctrine: And who can ſpeak or fight in defence of ſuch a Power? But that part we may well ſwear: For, 'tis no more than to ſwear ſhe had all Regal Power; and among the reſt, a Legal Power, inherent in her as Queen, to execute thoſe Laws; which, being a Truth, we may defend, without holding it reaſonable for her to uſe or exerciſe it: As we truly ſay, a Man hath Power or Ability, to do both Reaſonable and Unreaſonable Things; but deny, that he hath reaſon, or a reaſonable power to do theſe latter, and we only ſwear to defend that ſhe hath a Power or Ablity given her by Law, to deſtroy what is by us, not by them, eſteem'd Chriſtian Faith or certain Truth. Or it may be ſaid that they never intended to give the King a Power to deſtroy Chriſt's true Faith or any Truth: not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65377:38"/> conſequently to deſtroy our perſwaſion of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s purely Spiritual Authority in <hi>England,</hi> and other Dominions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Chriſt: Or that they gave him a Power to deſtroy ours, only in ſuppoſition of no ſuch Authority in the <hi>Pope;</hi> which ſuppoſition being falſe, they gave no Power to deſtroy our belief of it: and hence we ſwear not that the King hath ſuch a Power.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A ſixth is, becauſe moſt think that Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi> (who were ſuch knowing and good Men, that it would be very hard to imagin they either miſunderſtood or acted amiſs) died for not taking this Oath: And all know that our <hi>Catholick</hi> predeceſſors from the time it was made till our times, conſtantly refus'd it, which they would not have done, in caſe they had not thought it deny'd either ſome Article of their Faith, or at leaſt, ſome <hi>Theological</hi> or otherwiſe certain Truth. At leaſt, the Firſt of thoſe, who liv'd and talk'd with thoſe that made this Oath, had better Opportunites to know the ſenſe of it than we: and ſo we have more reaſon to ſtand to their Judgments than our own. As to the Firſt part, 'tis certain that Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Fiſher,</hi> died long before our Oath was made; to wit, in King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> days: when as ours was not made till the firſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and ſo could not die for refuſing what was not made till after they were dead. Nay, they were both dead before either of the two Oaths of Supremacy, made in the days of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> were enacted. What then they truly died for, was for ſpeaking (as it was pretended at leaſt) againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eight</hi>'s being <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> which is quite different from being <hi>Governour of the Realm;</hi> or at leaſt, more apt to bear a falſe ſence; and they had reaſon to fear the King meant to aſſume by thoſe words, an undue Power, becauſe he would not be contented with the fair play of the Explication <hi>quantum per Legem Dei licet,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:65377:38"/> added in the Convocation, by Biſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi>'s means; who, that explication being added, concurred to the Title of Head of the Church with the reſt; the equivalent whereof we have to ours, and that by Act of Parliament. But Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> diſliking what they diſlik't, made it Law that the Act that gave her Father that Title ſhould remain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd, and left thoſe Words <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> out of the Oath; and ſo our caſe is neither the ſame, nor like theirs. Beſides, it is not clear that either of them did dye for refuſing to acknowledge <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi>'s very Headſhip attributed to him by an Act of Parliament, made indeed before their Death, but during their Impriſonment. For 'tis certain they were both Impriſon'd on that very day, wherein <hi>Elizabeth Barton,</hi> called the Holy Maid of <hi>Kent,</hi> was Executed: and that the cauſe of their Impriſonment was, for refuſing then the Oath lately before enacted for acknowledging the King's Marriage with Queen <hi>Ann</hi> lawful, and her Iſſue, the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then born, lawfully begotten, or true Heir of the Crown, (vid. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derum dep. Schiſ. Anglicano.</hi> l. 1. p. 86. <hi>edit. Ingolſtad.)</hi> Moreover, it is known, that very great Saints dy'd in mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Errors. And that ſuch Errors did not prejudice their Sanctity, nor Martyrdom either. Witneſs S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> of <hi>Affrick,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="10">10. As to the Second, I confeſs, thoſe who liv'd in the Parliament's Dayes, which enacted the Oath, might have underſtood the Senſe of the Oath, as well, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I: For, who am I that I ſhould pretend to have as good or better Underſtanding, than any of them had? Next, I ſay, that the firſt of them, at leaſt, had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a better Opportunity, by diſcourſing with that Part of the Parliament that worded the Oath and Act; which perhaps, only knew the Meaning of both, better than other Folks. Yet, whether they, or at leaſt, more
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65377:39"/> than a few of them, went this way to work, is not a thing that we have any knowledg of; and, if they did not uſe this Means, we are upon equal Terms with them, or rather better. For, we have the Oath, and all Statutes concerning it, as well as they had: And, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, have ſeveral Treatiſes writ on both ſides, which they had not. But, as many have better Judgments, and better Opportunities to underſtand Divinity, Philoſophy, or Law, than others, and yet fall ſhort of Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo well as they, either by not looking at all, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlightly, the wrong way, or not hap'ning to think of ſo good Reaſons as others do: ſo, it may happen in our Caſe, as well as it hap'ned in the Caſe of the Oath of Allegiance; which, neither as to the Senſe of the Words, nor the Truth of that Senſe, ſeem'd to be nigh ſo well underſtood formerly, by thoſe that liv'd with its Makers, as by us that live now. Nay, ſome fancy'd no leſs than Three Hereſies in it, which Ghoſts have ſince diſappeared; and more than one is not now ſo much as pretended to be in that Oath. And the Excellent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Three Treatiſes of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> writ againſt that Oath, ſhews plainly, there is neither Hereſie nor Error in it, but honeſt and juſt Duty to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign.</p>
               <p n="11">11. This being ſo, the Queſtion ought to be, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us do actually ſee beſt into this Matter? And ſince neither We nor They could ſee into it, but by the Reaſons brought on both ſides, thoſe of us muſt be judg'd to ſee beſt into the Senſe of the VVords, who bring the beſt Reaſons. Now, thoſe I have here brought for the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Paſtoral, or purely Spiritual Power of the Keys not being excluded, ſhew to me far better than any I find them bring, to prove the contrary: And it is moſt likely, they brought the beſt Reaſons they had, as they
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65377:39"/> uſe to do in other Matters. But, though they had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they did produce, and alſo better than theſe I have produc'd, yet, ſince I know not that they had them, and alſo think it moſt likely they had them not, it is all one to me; who being able to conſider Reaſons on both ſides, may act according to the beſt Reaſon I can get; it being unreaſonable for a Man that can judg of Reaſon, to be guided by other Men's Judgments far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they <hi>have,</hi> or, which is all one, <hi>produce</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The Suppoſal of which in them, ſhewing them the way, is the only Reaſon why others ſhould be guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them: For, why ſhould one be guided by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that knows the way no better than he, and in our Caſe worſe? Moreover, the adhering to Predeceſſors Opinions, what ever Reaſon there be againſt them, is a certain way for the World, never to get out of any Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, unleſs our Fore-Fathers be ſuppos'd to be alwayes Infallible; the Contrary to which, frequent Experience has ſhewn. So that, this Argument of blindly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Fore-Fathers in Things ſubject to Reaſon; which ſeem'd ſo Plauſible at firſt, will be found, when well look't into, of a moſt pernicious Conſequence.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Neither is the leaving of their <hi>Judgment</hi> in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, the leaving of their Faith. For, unleſs we will wrong them, by making them hold for Faith what was not Faith, they could hold nothing of Faith but what was taught, or rather in this caſe given, by Chriſt. And ſo much we hold as well as they, and conceive the Oath does not at all touch it. In this indeed we may differ from them, who might think it does. But, whether ſuch words mean ſo or ſo, is far from a queſtion of Faith. Tis at moſt a difference in Opinion about the meaning of a Law, ſuch a difference as every body has almoſt with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65377:40"/> every body, and which, if it were not unblamable, there would be no living without blame in the world, where there always has and always will be, as many Opinions as heads. If we be in the right, as the reaſons alledged perſwade us we are, nothing can be more prepoſterouſly alledged againſt us then their Example. For, they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the dictates of their Conſcience, and we ſhould go againſt ours? They had indeed renounc't their Faith if they had taken the Oath in Caſe they were perſwaded, though untruly, that it did deny their Faith; we cannot renounce Faith by taking the Oath while we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it meddles not with Faith; no, though our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion ſhould happen to be falſe; but we ſhould plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe to do our duty, which we think the Oath only requires. In ſhort, they did well and we ſhould do ill.</p>
               <p n="13">13. But perchance they and we may not differ even in this Opinion. For it doth not follow, They deny'd the Oath, therefore they thought the Oath denyed Faith. For they might think the Oath deny'd ſome other truth or Probability, which they thought they could not, and ſo would not forſwear. For Example, they might think it true or probable, that the Queen was not Temporal Governour in Spiritual or mixt Cauſes, and over Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Perſons; becauſe they might think it true, or probable, that theſe Cauſes and Perſons were exempted, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> from Secular Juriſdiction, and did belong to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as many do at this Day; and others might think, the <hi>Pope</hi> had a direct or indirect Temporal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to depoſe the King, either by Divine Right of <hi>Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumque ligaveris,</hi> &amp;c. or by the Title of King <hi>John</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And hence, could not ſwear, they thought no ſuch thing. But hence ariſes.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:65377:40"/>14. A Seventh Scruple, How one may lawfully ſwear theſe things are falſe, which one doth not know to be ſo? And how can any know them to be ſo, when he ſees great Scholars hold the contrary? For a full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this, I remit the Reader to the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Jeſuits Loyalty,</hi> and the Second Treatiſe of it. In ſhort, I reply, That of thoſe, who held theſe Things to be Falſe, ſome think they certainly knew them to be ſo; and theſe certainly may ſwear they are ſo. Others hold them to be ſo; but are Conſcious to themſelves, that they hold this upon Reaſons only more probable, than are brought for the other ſide; and though theſe may not lawfully ſwear they are falſe, yet they may ſwear, that they are ſo in their Judgment or Conſcience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that they are ſo in their Judgment, is certainly true. And this is all the Oath doth or can reaſonably require of the Generality of thoſe, unto whom it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd; they being able to ſay and ſwear, what they hold in theſe Queſtions; and not able to ſay or ſwear they certainly know what they hold to be true. And this is ſufficient for ſecuring Allegiance; ſince People uſe not to act contrary to what they hold, though they hold it upon probable Reaſons only: On the other ſide, thoſe that are certainly or probably perſwaded they are true, cannot ſwear they are, ſo much as in their Judgment or Conſcience, falſe; and ſo cannot take this Oath. But I judge, they may find Reaſon enough to alter their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if they read late Authors upon this Subject, to whom I remit them.</p>
               <p n="15">15. And in this caſe we make a Schiſm, (as ſome are pleaſed to call it, to fright Timorous Conſciences which are us'd to abhor the horrible Sin, which that word moſt commonly ſignifies) or Diviſion only in Opinion; which is certainly known, and confeſſed to be in other Caſes,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65377:41"/> lawful. And, I hope, they will not argue, that thoſe who leave their <hi>Opinions,</hi> will alſo leave their <hi>Faith;</hi> there being no Conſequence from one to the other. All the Schools, that is in a manner, all the Teaching Part of the Church, make Schiſms daily, and are divided from one another in this Senſe; and, which is more, are never likely to leave this kind of Schiſmatizing, and return to an Union; or rather, 'tis impoſſible they ſhould. For, how can it be expected, that in Things depending on Opinions, Men's Fancies, Tempers, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their Judgment ſhould light to be the ſame? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we condemn our Pious Anceſtors, (as ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) but applaud their Fortitude, who chooſe rather to die, than to ſwear a thing which they thought either falſe or oppoſite, if not to <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> at leaſt to Truth. What we condemn, is only their Opinions; and this upon better Reaſons againſt them, than they brought for them. And who can condemn us for this? or look upon us the worſe for receding from them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Terms, as every good Man is bound to recede from his former ſelf?</p>
               <p n="16">16. An Eighth Objection is, That be it how it will, whether former Catholicks, ſince Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Days, had reaſon to do what they did or no, or the Oath in it ſelf contains the King's juſt Right or no; yet now, the conſtant taking the Oath by Proteſtants, and refuſing it by Catholicks; and this for ſo conſiderable a Tract of Time, is become a Diſtinctive Signe between Catholicks and Proteſtants; and ſo, the Taking it implyes a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of Faith, which conſequently muſt needs be Scandalous and Unlawful? I anſwer, Signes are but of two ſorts, <hi>Extrinſecal,</hi> which appertain not to the Thing at all, but are meerly Arbitrary; as that of the <hi>Jews</hi> wearing a Yellow Hat at <hi>Rome:</hi> Or elſe, <hi>Intrinſecal,</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:65377:41"/> which are connected with the very Nature of the Thing; And this either as Cauſe with Effect, as the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Ears of Corn is a Signe of Harveſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching; or as Effect with Cauſe, as Smoak is a Signe of Fire: Or, laſtly, as one Part ſeen, is a Signe of the Preſence of the Whole, with which 'tis connected. One of theſe Kinds of Signes, then, the taking this Oath muſt be, or 'tis none at all. Again, it can be but one of them, they being contradiſtinguiſh't to one another. Firſt then, if it be <hi>only</hi> an <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Signe of being a Proteſtant, then it muſt be ſaid, that there is no Harm in it at all, taking it <hi>as in it ſelf,</hi> nor does it at all relate to Faith; which yet is contrary to the Sentiment of all thoſe who oppos'd the Oath hitherto, and the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of former Catholicks, who refus'd to take it: Nay, I much fear, to the Judgment likewiſe of our preſent Objecters, however they are pleas'd, that they may make ſomething of this Objection, to lay it aſide. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the ſwearing to a Form of Words which have a meaning under them either true or falſe, and expreſs ſome Tenets (either relating or not relating to Faith) is a very odd thing to make an Extrinſecal ſign of. Meer ſounds may ſerve for Extrinſecal marks to diſtinguiſh Parrats, but words made to expreſs mens Conceptions, will neceſſarily reach their Minds, and affect their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, or have ſomething <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> in them, and ſo if they judge differently of their meaning, will <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> them <hi>Intrinſecally,</hi> do we all we can. Secondly, to alledge in this Occaſion, that the Taking this Oath is any kind of <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> ſign, that is either Cauſe, Effect or a Part of Proteſtant Religion as diſtinguiſht from <hi>Catholick,</hi> is as voyd of reaſon as the other, unleſs we beg the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and ſuppoſe it granted to our hands that the Oath contains a ſence oppoſit to <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith; without which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65377:42"/> prov'd or admitted, 'tis impoſſible to pretend, 'tis a ſign Intrinſecally diſtinguiſhing thoſe two parties. Truth is, theſe Objecters ſhould ſay that 'tis only an Extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sign, if the nature of the Thing would permit them; for if it have an Intrinſecal Connexion with any Tenet contrary to the Religion of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> it muſt neceſſarily be, (even in their own opinion) <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> and ſo, the Refuſal of it ſhould, as all ſolid reaſon requires, be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled upon it's Oppoſition to what they judge <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, and not on it's being a bare Sign of Proteſtant Religion; and this a pittiful one too, as never having been conſtituted ſuch by any Publick Authority, but meerly taken up by the ill-grounded Fancies of private men.</p>
               <p n="17">17. But, ſay they, we abſtract whether the Oath bear a good or bad ſenſe, and affirm that even taking it in this abſtractive State, 'tis a Diſtinctive Signe. I reply, 'Tis very hard, when one takes an Oath, to abſtract whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it have a good or bad Senſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and therefore, I much doubt, it will not paſs current. Chriſtianity, that an Oath, which conſiſts of Words that have a Meaning in them, ſhould bear a Conſideration which is indifferent to a good or bad Meaning. Beſides, I like this Abſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worſe than any part of the Diſcourſe: For, it ſeems to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify thus much, Let the Words import only a juſt Duty to my Prince, or how you will; yet, if our Anceſtors have refus'd to pay their Allegiance, by taking this Oath when lawfully adminiſtred, I will prefer their Example before my own Duty.</p>
               <p n="18">18. And, as 'tis impoſſible, to rank the taking this Oath, under either Head of a Diſtinctive Signe, ſo 'tis moſt evident, it is not held for ſuch. For firſt, (to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Laws and Law-makers, of which enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove) the moſt Learned Proteſtant Authors before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65377:42"/> who interpret the Oath conſiſtently with our Faith, and as many as read, approve and abet them, (which includes Princes, and the generality of the moſt Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Men of our Nation) cannot hold it, to argue a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of one Religion from another. Next, the Teſt propos'd heretofore, to incapacitate <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> from bearing any Offices; which imports a renouncing <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> and other Points, plainly ſhews, they did not think the taking this Oath diſtinguiſh't them from <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Again, which of our Neighbours, ſeeing thoſe who take the Oaths live in all other Regards like <hi>Catholicks,</hi> judges them, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> upon the taking them, to become <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> Not one. It remains then, that only our ſelves fancy to our ſelves, 'tis a Diſtinctive Signe, and cry it up for ſuch, and are only ſeconded by ſome few others, who hear how fiercely our weaker Brethren inveigh againſt thoſe who take it, as Hereticks. And ſuch Diſtinctive Signes as theſe, we ſhould have had good ſtore, had it not pleas'd God to raiſe from time to time, ſome few good Men, who lov'd Truth ſo well, as to dare to be Honeſt. Had it not been for <hi>Widdrington,</hi> and one or two more, the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> would ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have got to be a <hi>Diſtinctive Signe</hi> too, and the <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power</hi> an eminent One. No fewer than three Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies were ſaid to be in that Oath; and certainly, that which contains three Hereſies, deſerves with far better Right to be made a Diſtinctive Signe, than the Oath of Supremacy, which was thought to contain but One at moſt. Now, the Pretence of ſuch Diſtinctive Signes as theſe, is ſo far from deterring Ingenuous Men from wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt it, that it rather induces an obligation in them to oppoſe with Reaſon, the loud inſignificant Noiſe, which ſtuns ſo many: The Honour of our <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Faith, and the Duty to our Prince and State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65377:43"/> both concern'd, that ſuch ill grounded Pretences do not get Head. And as for the Scandal, which they will needs <hi>take</hi> when none <hi>gives</hi> it, and <hi>raiſe</hi> by their Noiſe, when by uſing calm Reaſon they might <hi>ſettle</hi> it, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who tells them; <hi>Melius est ut ſcandalum ortatar quam at verum non dicatur. 'Tis better Scandal ſhould ariſe, than Truth not to be told.</hi> And to St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquin,</hi> who ſayes; <hi>Ob nullam ſcandalum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquenda eſt veritatis defenſio: The Patronage of Truth is not to be left off for any Scandal whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. The laſt Scruple ariſeth from the Conſideration of all that hath been hitherto ſaid: For, after all this Diſpute, it is not abſolutely impoſſible but that the Oath might have been intended by the Makers of it, to deny the <hi>Pope</hi>'s purely Spiritual Power of the Keys, even in any Caſe or Contingency in <hi>England,</hi> and other his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions; though we have ſhewn this to be altogether improbable; and, hence, peradventure, they do actually deny it, who take this Oath. But, I anſwer, That notwithſtanding what Poſſibility of Truth ſoever there be in the Antecedent, there is no danger at all of the Conſequent: For, I am as certain as that I live, and know my own Thoughts, that I underſtand the Words in a Senſe not oppoſite either to <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, or to any Truth whatſoever. Next, I am certain I take the Oath in that Senſe only in which I underſtand it: And hence, I am certain likewiſe, that I deny not my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, or any other Truth. Only, I may perchance have ſome ſmall Doubt, (as I may have of the Words of many Publick Oaths in the World, which are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding generally held to be lawfully taken) whether the Senſe I take them in, be meant by Law. But, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Matter be, or whether I doubt, or not doubt, in any manner at all, ſure I am, I do not ſwear this doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65377:43"/> thing; to wit, than my Senſe of them is given by Law; but only acknowledge upon Oath, that the Senſe I have of them is, in or according to my judgment, True.</p>
               <p n="20">20. And hence, I am induc'd to believe, if theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould help to effect a general Perſwaſion, that the Oath means not to exclude the Pope's, or other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prelates Paſtoral Power in all Contingencies, that then, after ſuch a general Perſwaſion, the Oath may be lawfully and freely taken. In the mean time, becauſe no tenderneſs can be too great in ſuch matters, to avoid giving Offence to any, whether of our own or of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Communion, who, if they underſtand the Oath otherwiſe, will be apt to judge according to their own Apprehenſion, that to take the Oath is to renounce the Religion which the Taker profeſſeth: I conceive it adviſable, that who takes it declare plainly before-hand, in what Senſe he underſtands it; <hi>viz.</hi> that he takes it not in the moſt large Senſe of the Words, which might ſeem to ſome to deny his Religion; but only in that Senſe, which to the beſt of his Judgment is aſſign'd it <hi>by Law;</hi> or in that Senſe in which Learned Proteſtants, allow'd and approv'd by Publick Authority, have expounded it, and underſtood it to be the Law-Senſe of it; or that he underſtands the Power meant by the Law to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd in the King, is the Power of the Sword, not of the Keys: Likewiſe, that the Keys are not deny'd to the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other Forreign Prelate, but the Sword. Or rather, becauſe the Power of the Keys has been ſtretch't by ſome to Temporals, to the diſpoſing even of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and ſuch like Exorbitancies; which have not only been claim'd but practis'd, and the Power to do them all the while call'd the <hi>Power of the Keys;</hi> it were fit to make this Declaration in words not liable to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65377:44"/> For which, I know none more proper, than thoſe before mention'd of the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Armagh;</hi> that the King only has the Supreme, External, Coac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juriſdiction, or Power of the Sword, within his Dominions, over all Perſons, and in all Things or Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and that no Forreign Prelate either has, or ought to have any Part thereof: and that he underſtands the Oath ſo, and no otherwiſe, and ſo takes it. By this means he will deal uprightly, and candidly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameably before God and Man, and without any Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Offence or Scandal, whether to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:65377:44"/>
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HAving been longer than I intended, I conceive it not amiſs to take a ſhort view of what has been ſaid, at parting. The whole in Truth lies in a narrow compaſs: who refuſes the Oath, for what concerns the <hi>Pope,</hi> muſt either think that his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Power is deny'd by it; or that what without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is deny'd, <hi>viz,</hi> That External Coercive Judiciary Power, which he has in ſome other Princes Dominions, and heretofore had here, is ſo his right, that it can by no Humane Power be taken away. There is no more in the Caſe. For, as to what relates to the King, I take it to be very clear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the Firſt, the expreſſions of the Oath are ſo general, that who looks upon them as they lie there, and judges according to their bare ſound, has reaſon to except againſt them; ſo much reaſon, that were they taken out, and digeſted into Propoſitions, to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and judged of purely by the import of the Terms, perhaps there is not a Catholick in the World, at leaſt I believe there are but very few, who would approve them. In likelihood our Anceſtors, who refus'd the Oath, lookt upon them no otherwiſe; which I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believe, becauſe I ſee that many, I think the moſt, go no farther at this day. And then 'tis no wonder that <hi>They</hi> refus'd, and <hi>Theſe</hi> condemn it. All Catholicks generally would refuſe and condemn it too, if they lookt upon it in the ſame manner.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But who look upon the ſame expreſſions, as part of an Oath contained in an Act, and reflect that the Oath is declared to be for the <hi>better Obſervation and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65377:45"/> of that Act;</hi> and therefore, and in force of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule of underſtanding words according to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpoken of, ought to be underſtood only of what the Act ſpeaks: That all the Power, of which the Act ſpeaks, is Power <hi>repugnant to the Antient Juriſdiction of the Crown;</hi> Power both <hi>Forreign and Uſurped;</hi> Power <hi>burthenſome and intolerably chargeable to the Subject:</hi> That this Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not only in the Title, and Preamble, but in the very Branch which aboliſhes the Popes Power, where the intent is particularly expreſt to be, that <hi>All uſurped and forraign power be forever extinguiſh't:</hi> That the Popes Paſtoral Power, if it may be called <hi>Forreign</hi> cannot be thought <hi>Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,</hi> by a Chriſtian who reads the Scripture, and ſees S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in him his Succeſſor, 'empower'd there and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt to feed his Sheep: That, where a Law declares it's own intent, 'tis not for others to think it intended more, or otherwiſe then as it declares: That no more was extinguiſht, then was intended to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſht, with what elſe is ſaid in the foregoing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; may find reaſon to judge, that the Meaning of the Words of the Oath is not altogether ſo large as their Sound, and that all the Power deny'd there ſignifies no more than all the Power ſpoken of in the Act; and, therefore, that Paſtoral Power is not renounc't; that which is renounc't being limited by the Act to <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> and <hi>Uſurped,</hi> and to <hi>Soveraignty-repugnant</hi> Power.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Again, who conſiders that the Oath Actually is underſtood in this manner by thoſe of greateſt note in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> That Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> tells us (Schiſm Guarded p. 311.) That by this Act there <hi>is no forreign Power aboliſhed, but only that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Ancient Laws of England, and to the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal:</hi> p. 340. That <hi>Juriſdiction purely Spiritual</hi> (the ſame which I call Paſtoral) <hi>doth neither diſinherit the</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:65377:45"/> 
                  <hi>Prince nor the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers, nor deſtroy and Annul the Laws and Prerogative Royal, nor vex the Kings Liege people, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh the Subject, nor drain the Kingdom of its Treaſures,</hi> &amp;c. infint, is not guilty of any of the grievances of which our Laws complain. <hi>It is the external Regiment of the Church by new Roman Laws,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that are apparently guilty of all theſe evils. Theſe Papal Innovations we have taken away indeed—more than theſe Innovations we have taken nothing away, that I know of:</hi> page 353. <hi>We have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noanced the Subſtance of the Papacy, except the ſubſtance of the Papacy do conſiſt in coactive Power:</hi> who conſiders beſides that theſe things are not whiſper'd in Corners, but own'd in the face of the World; nor the private fancies of a ſingle man, (his Book being lately Reprinted after the Authors Death, with the countenance of more conſiderable Authority than Books uſually have, and the ſame may be ſaid of the other Proteſtant Authors above-cited) will find himſelf put to it, if he be urged, to make out how he comes to pretend to underſtand the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Proteſtant Laws, better than Proteſtants themſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It may very well be, that a Proteſtant may be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſwear, what a Catholick cannot: becauſe one may think true, what the other does not: But, where they both agree in the thing, and what the Proteſtant means when he ſwears, the Catholick thinks true as well as he, and yet will not ſwear the ſame truth in the ſame words, looks like a Riddle. If the words <hi>All Power</hi> ſignify <hi>All Uſurped Power</hi> to a Proteſtant, I ſee not but they may ſignify the ſame to a Catholick too. And, if it be known that he means by them as the Proteſtant does, 'tis plain, They cannot ſignify otherwiſe. For the ſignification of words is nothing but the known mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe who uſe them. And though they ſhould ſignify otherwiſe elſewhere, they can ſignify no more but
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65377:46"/> ſo, where 'tis known no more but ſo is meant by them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This difficulty then, in two words, is only this: Whether <hi>All Power</hi> in the Oath means abſolutely All, or <hi>All the Power mentioned and intended by the Act,</hi> for the obſervation whereof the Oath was made. That Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral words are ordinarily, I had almoſt ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, confin'd by Circumſtances, is a thing ſo known, that 'tis impertinent perhaps to mention; at leaſt, to bring examples of it. Whether <hi>Thoſe</hi> words are confin'd in <hi>This</hi> Caſe, is all we have to conſider, and to every mans Judgment and Conſcience I leave it. Only who is not ſatisfy'd with what has been ſaid, has ſtill I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, a ſafe way of proceeding, by declaring before hand, if he take the Oath, that he takes it in the ſenſe of the Law, as underſtood by all Proteſtant Writers, none excepted, particularly Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhal;</hi> which, as was ſhown, ſeems to amount to a Conſent of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; After which I for my part ſee no cauſe of Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple remaining for the firſt Point.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For the ſecond, who is perſwaded that the Power Renounc'd by the Oath, does indeed belong to the Pope by Divine Right, (For what is ſettled by Human, may by Human Authority be unſettled) undoubtedly cannot take the Oath. But he ſhould do well to conſider, how he comes to be ſo perſwaded. This is no place to treat the Queſtion: I ſhall only ſay, that, if any one take that Perſwaſion for Faith, he is certainly miſtaken; and that many of the moſt Learned among Catholicks are miſtaken too, if it be true. It is a Power which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore has drawn perpetual complaints from our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Anceſtors, and many Laws for Redreſs of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies they ſuffer'd by it. It is a Power for whoſe ſake our Religion is at this day aſpers'd with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65377:46"/> of Inconſiſtence with the Eaſe of Subjects, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Common-wealth. Who will maintain it, engages himſelf to clear it from theſe Objections. For, if he do not, he will not clear himſelf from doing his part to bring his Country again into what the Law calls Bondage, and his Religion into the Scandalous ſhame of being indeed guilty of what is laid to her Charge. No man can go about it, without maintaining in the firſt place that our Catholick Anceſtors complained always without cauſe, and felt nothing when they cry'd out of the burthen. If They had reaſon to complain, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have none to endure what they complained of, nor can Catholicks of all men expect they ſhould.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In ſhort, there is nothing does more harm in the world then miſtaken Zeal, which, under a miſtaken pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion, we ſee tranſports Men to things the moſt contrary to Religion that can be. 'Tis not to be thought that in our Communion there is no Humane Frailty. Opinions have been broacht concerning the Pope, and are to this day maintained, prejudicial, to ſay no more, both to the Soveraignty of Princes, and Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy of the Church. Whether the Power in queſtion to exerciſe an independent, Soveraign, Coactive, Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Authority, in all Princes Dominions, and all Biſhops Dioceſſes, upon the matter to govern the Church and World alone, be not of the number, They ſhould do well to conſider, who refuſe the Oath for it's ſake. For if it be, their Zeal is plainly a miſtaken Zeal; which, as it uſes to do, deceives and carries them juſt contrary to what they mean, the Scandal, and, to their Power, ruine of Religion, which they think to preſerve. For my part I beg of God the grace rather to ſuffer the loſs of my own life, than deny the Pope, or any man any juſt right; and I beg the ſame grace to preſerve me
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65377:47"/> from abetting unjuſt things even in the Pope. Time has been when England has ſeen three Hundred Forreigners ſent over at once, by the Power in queſtion, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of the firſt Vacant Benefices. I ſhould think my ſelf neither good Engliſh-man, nor good Chriſtian, if I ſhould obſtinately ſtand for a Power to commit ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65377:47"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
